Alright, I'd like to get started.
好的，我想开始了。
Today I will talk about virtual machines.
今天我将谈论虚拟机。
And I'm gonna lecture is really going to be divided into three pieces,
我要讲的课会分成三个部分，
one is going to start with what's called trap and emulate virtualization,
第一部分是所谓的 trap 和模拟虚拟化，
which is basically an overview of how you could build your own virtual machine scheme
它描述了如何构建自己的虚拟机方案，
RISC-V in QEMU,
比如 RISC-V 在 QEMU 中，
then I'm gonna talk a bit about
然后我要讨论一下，
recent hardware support and microprocessors for virtualization,
最近的支持虚拟化的硬件和微处理器，
and then about today's paper Dune
然后是关于今天的论文 Dune ，
which uses this modern hardware support.
它使用了这种现代的硬件支持。
Alright, so first, what is a virtual machine,
好的，那么首先什么是虚拟机，
it's really you can think of it as a simulation of a computer,
你可以把它想象成一台计算机的模拟，
that's accurate enough to run an operating system,
它的精确度足以运行操作系统，
so QEMU is a, a example of
所以 QEMU 是一个例子，
you could consider to be an example of a virtual machine,
你可以认为是一个虚拟机的例子，
the way I'm going to talk about it is that,
我要说的是，
down at the lowest level sitting on top of the hardware,
位于硬件之上的最底层，
we're gonna imagine a virtual machine monitor or VMM,
我们想象一个虚拟机监视器或 VMM ，
and this more or less takes the place of the standard operating system kernel,
这或多或少取代了标准操作系统内核，
and the virtual machine monitor's job is
虚拟机监视器的工作是
to simulate a bunch of computers for guest operating systems,
为客户操作系统模拟一组计算机，
so said, appear in in you know what used to be user space in our usual diagrams,
所以，在我们通常的表中，在用户空间中，
but has now guest space.
但现在有了客户空间。
So this is we call this guest space
这里是的客户空间，
and down here host space.
在这里下面是主机空间。
We're gonna have a bunch of, one or more guest operating systems kernels,
我们会有一个或多个客户操作系统内核，
so we might have a Linux kernel as one guest,
我们可能有一个 Linux 内核作为一个客户内核，
and this Linux kernel is gonna
而这个 Linux 内核，
you know it's just it thinks of itself as an ordinary kernel,
它只是认为自己是一个普通的内核，
and it runs a bunch of processes,
它运行一系列进程，
maybe VI and a C compiler.
可能是 VI 和 C 编译器。
Then we might have other guest,
然后我们可能会有其他客户机，
I have other guest two guest virtual machines running here,
我有其他客户机在这里运行，
there might be maybe another Linux
也许有另一个 Linux ，
or maybe even some other operating system like Windows,
甚至可能是 Windows 这样的其他操作系统，
all running on the same machine,
都在同一台机器上运行，
and there would be windows processes running
并且有 Windows 进程运行，
within as within this guest operating system.
在这个客户机操作系统中。
So the host, the host world where the virtual machine monitor runs,
所以虚拟机监视器运行的地方是主机世界，
and guest world where these ordinary operating systems run,
这些普通操作系统运行的是客户机世界，
and furthermore, we're going to talk about a lot about in
此外，我们还会讲到很多，
within the guest world, a guest supervisor mode which is mode that kernels running,
在客户机世界中，客户机管理程序是内核运行的模式，
the guest kernels running at guest user mode.
客户机内核运行在客户用户模式。
And again, the the kind of classical goal of virtual machine monitor is
同样，虚拟机监视器的一般目标是，
to provide an emulation of a machine,
为了提供机器的模拟，
that's so good,
这很好，
that you can just boot ordinary Linux, ordinary Windows unmodified
你可以不加修改地启动普通的 Linux ，普通的 Windows ，
and have it run inside this virtual machine,
并让它在这个虚拟机内运行，
never suspecting that anything funny is going on.
永远不用怀疑会有什么奇怪的事情发生。
So, for example, the virtual machine monitor has to be in a position
所以，虚拟机监视器必须位于
to emulate the difference between supervisor mode and user mode in a way
在某种程度上模拟主管模式和用户模式之间的差异，
that is just completely convincing simulation of how the actual hardware does it,
它完全模拟实际硬件的工作，
even though that's,
即使那是，
you can't really be exactly what's going on,
你不可能真的是这样，
so that's why we talk about guest supervisor mode and guest user mode,
这就是我们讨论的客户机管理者模式和客户机用户模式，
VMM's emulation of those two modes.
VMM 对这两种模式进行模拟。
So so why would you want to use a virtual machine,
那么你为什么要使用虚拟机，
it turns out there's a lot of reasons
有很多原因，
to run lots of a distinct guest operating systems on a single computer,
在一台计算机上运行许多不同的客户操作系统，
sometimes maybe you're running a big company
也许你在经营一家大公司，
and you, you need to have lots and lots of servers,
你需要很多很多的服务器，
maybe you know name servers and security servers, who knows what
也许域名服务器和安全服务器，或者其他的，
and each one of them doesn't use many resources,
而且它们中的每一个都不会使用太多的资源，
so it's sort of a waste of time to have to buy a physical machine for it,
所以为它购买一台物理机器有点浪费时间，
but you want to run, you know you want to
但是你想要运行，
run lots of these low intensity servers on a single piece of hardware,
想在单个硬件上运行大量这样的低强度服务器，
you can save money by using a virtual machine.
你可以通过使用虚拟机来省钱。
It turns out virtual machines are also very, very widely used in cloud computing
虚拟机在云计算中的应用也非常非常广泛，
where it's an outfit like Amazon Amazon AWS,
比如一个像亚马逊 AWS 这样的机构，
they don't want to rent out physical machines to people,
他们不想把实体机租给人们，
because that turns out to be a difficult to manage,
因为这是一个很难管理的，
what they want to do is rent their customers, their cloud customers
他们想要做的是租给他们的客户，
just a machine that Amazon can on the fly you know decide what hardware run it on
一台机器，亚马逊决定在什么硬件上运行，
whether to run a bigger or smaller machine,
是运行一台大一点还是小一点的机器，
Amazon can decide,
亚马逊可以决定，
you know, it's a it's current customers,
这是目前的客户，
maybe there's two customers on this piece of hardware right here,
也许在这块硬件上有两个客户，
but they're not using the computer very much,
但是他们不太使用计算机，
maybe it can pack a third or fourth customer onto that same piece of hardware
也许它可以把第三个第四个客户放到同一台硬件上，
without spending extra money, but get more revenue.
不花费额外的成本，但是可以获得更多的收入。
So this virtual machines allow kind of extra level of flexibility
所以，这个虚拟机提供了某种额外的灵活性，
and you know it's kind of trick that's being used is
这是一种使用的技巧，
that we're kind of shifting up the existing operating system kernels and user space
我们提升现有的操作系统内核和用户空间，
and adding a new layer underneath to provide this flexibility.
并且在下面增加一个新的层来提供这种灵活性。
It turns out there's there's other reasons why people use virtual machines,
人们使用虚拟机还有其他原因，
one is certainly kernel development,
一个当然是内核开发，
which is why we all use QEMU,
这就是为什么我们使用 QEMU ，
the ability to run xv6 in a kind of virtual environment,
一种在虚拟环境中运行 xv6 的能力，
rather than a real computer,
而不是在真实计算机中，
makes this course much more convenient for all of us,
使这门课程对我们所有人都更方便，
it also makes it a little bit easier to debug,
它还使调试变得更容易，
because we can turns out that
这是因为，
once you're running xv6 and this virtual machine environment,
一旦你运行 xv6 和这个虚拟机环境，
QEMU provides us easier to provide GDB access,
QEMU 使我们更容易提供 GDB 访问，
than it would be on a physical computer.
比起在一台物理计算机上。
And the final reason that people use virtual machines is that,
人们使用虚拟机的最后一个原因是，
there's a bunch of tricks that can be played
可以有很多技巧可以使用，
using this extra layer of indirection provided by the virtual machine monitor,
利用虚拟机监视器提供的这层额外的间接层，
for example, you can checkpoint an entire running operating system and user processes,
比如，你可以对整个正在运行的操作系统和用户进程设置检查点，
you can take a checkpoint of it,
你可以获取它的一个检查点，
stash it away somewhere maybe on disk,
将其隐藏在某个地方，比如磁盘上，
and then later restore that checkpoint,
然后恢复这个检查点，
sort of exactly the state of that operating system and its processes
完全相同的操作系统和进程，
as it was at the time of the checkpoint,
像它在检查点时那样，
it's useful for reliability for debugging
它对于调试可靠性，
for maybe cloning the image of a virtual machine,
对于克隆虚拟机的内存是有用的，
so you can run it multiple times.
所以你可以多次运行它。
Another game you can play is
另一个你可以玩的游戏是，
you can might migrate a guest an entire guest to another computer,
你可以把一个客户机迁移到另一台计算机上，
if you have a guest operating system running on a physical computer
如果你在物理计算机上运行客户机操作系统，
and you need to shut down or replace that physical computer,
你需要关闭或更换物理计算机，
you can actually turns out move the running virtual machine image
你可以移动正在运行的虚拟机映像，
without disturbing it to another physical computer,
在不干扰它的情况下，到另一台物理机上，
so that you can shut down the first one.
这样你就可以关闭第一个了。
There's just examples of why people really like virtual machines
这是一些例子，说明为什么人们喜欢虚拟机，
and people really do virtual machines are very, very widely used,
人们确实非常广泛地使用虚拟机，
and they also have a long history,
而且它们也有很长的历史，
this ideas first came up in the 1960s,
这个想法最早是在二十世纪六十年代提出的，
and they've been developed over time
它们是随着时间的推移而发展，
until they're, they're quite pervasive easy to use.
直到它们变得非常普遍，很容易使用。
For this course, the reason why we're looking into them is
对于这门课，我们调查它们的原因是，
that virtual machine monitors provide sort of different view
虚拟机监视器提供了一种不同的角度，
on what an operating system can be,
关于操作系统，
instead of the process abstraction we're all used to,
与我们习惯的进程抽象不同，
you know we have some analogous structures here,
我们这里有一些类似的结构，
but a sort of providing a different kind of container,
而是提供了一种不同类型的容器，
it's not a process, it's a sort of simulated machine,
它不是进程，而是一种模拟机器，
allows us to kind of think about all the stuff we've been talking about,
允许我们考虑我们讨论的所有东西，
memory allocation, scheduling protection, from a different point of view,
从不同的角度思考内存分配、调度保护，
maybe give us some ideas,
或许能给我们一些建议，
which we can take back to traditional operating system kernels,
我们可以带回到传统的操作系统内核，
and indeed much of the action
实际上很多方案，
sort of development design, development research action
开发设计、开发研究的方案，
has shifted from conventional kernels
已经从传统内核
down into the virtual machine monitors themselves,
向下转移到虚拟机监视器本身，
as they've gotten more and more prevalent,
随着它们变得越来越普遍，
so in some sense kind of the topic of operating systems
所以，在某种意义上，操作系统的话题
is drifting downwards a bit by one layer.
向下漂移了一层。
Okay, for the first part of this lecture I want to talk about
好的，这节课我想讨论的第一部分，
a bit about how we could implement our own virtual machine,
介绍一下我们如何实现自己的虚拟机，
and I'm gonna use RISC-V as that sort of,
我将使用 RISC-V 作为一种，
assume that we're trying to emulate RISC-V hardware,
假设我们正在尝试模拟 RISC-V 硬件，
so we can run operating systems designed for RISC-V xv6.
让我们可以运行为 RISC-V 设计的 xv6 操作系统。
And just to repeat the specific goals,
再重复一下具体的目标，
what we'd like we're for kind of classical virtual machines,
我们所希望的是一种典型的虚拟机，
what we'd like to build is
我们想要构建的是
something in which the guest software is just completely not aware,
客户机软件完全没有意识到，
that it's running inside a virtual machine,
它在虚拟机中运行，
we want to build something
我们想要构建一些东西，
that makes it impossible for the guest software to distinguish
使客户机软件不可能区分，
to decide whether is this am I running on a real machine or a virtual machine, right,
确定是在真实机器上运行还是在虚拟机上运行，
we want the emulation to be that good.
我们希望模拟能有那么好的效果。
And the reason for that is that we don't want,
原因是，我们不想，
we want to be able to,
我们希望能够，
we'd like to be able to run anything in our virtual machine,
我们希望能够在我们的虚拟机中运行任何东西，
any operating system even maybe an operating system we haven't heard of,
任何操作系统，甚至可能是我们没有听说过的操作系统，
and that means that you know,
这意味着，
whatever funny stuff the operating system does
无论操作系统做什么有趣的事情，
and the way it uses hardware,
无论它使用硬件的方式是什么，
the virtual machine has to provide that an emulation of exactly the hardware,
虚拟机必须提供精确的硬件模拟，
so that any tricks that work on the real hardware
所以，在真实硬件上起作用的任何技巧
are also going to work on the virtual machine.
也将在虚拟机上起作用。
Sort of similar goal that we'd like is,
我们想要的类似目标是，
we want there to be no way,
我们希望没有办法，
not only no way for a guest to decide if it's running on virtual machine,
不仅客户机无法决定它是否在虚拟机上运行，
but no way for guests to be able to escape from the virtual machine,
而且客户机也无法从虚拟机中逃脱，
a lot of the reason why people use virtual machines is
人们使用虚拟机的很多原因是
to provide strict confinement for untrusted software,
为了对不可信的软件提供严格的限制，
even untrusted operating systems running inside the virtual machine,
即使不可信操作系统在虚拟机中运行，
for example if you're Amazon and you're selling cloud servers,
比如，如果你是亚马逊，并且销售云服务器，
your customers often who provide the operating system
你的客户通常提供操作系统，
that runs on the virtual machine as well as the applications
在虚拟机上运行的（操作系统）和应用程序，
and gosh for all you know your customers are not running ordinary Linux,
天哪，你的客户不是在运行普通的 Linux ，
they're running a special hacked version of Linux,
他们正在运行一个特殊版本的 Linux ，
whose intended to try to break out of its virtual machine
他们试图突破它的虚拟机，
and break into Amazon's either the virtual machines of Amazon's or other customer's
并闯入亚马逊或其他用户的虚拟机，
or into the virtual machine monitor that Amazon uses to enforce isolation.
或者进入 Amazon 用来实施隔离的虚拟机监视器。
So, it's quite important
所以，这很重要，
that guest and not be able to break out of their virtual machines,
客户机不能突破它们的虚拟机，
they be able to use the memory,
它们能够使用内存，
that they're allowed to use by the virtual machine monitor, for example,
那些虚拟机监视器允许它们使用的内存，
but not other memory,
但不能使用其他内存，
similarly that they shouldn't be able to reach out
同样，它们不应该接触到，
without permission and use things like storage devices or network interface cards,
没有权限使用存储设备或网卡之类的东西，
so you're gonna have very strict isolation.
所以你有非常严格的隔离。
And in many ways
并且在许多方面
virtual machines provides stricter isolation than ordinary Unix processes,
虚拟机提供了比普通 Unix 进程更严格的隔离，
ordinary Unix processes can often interact,
普通的 Unix 进程通常可以交互，
they can kill each other
它们可以杀死对方，
or they can read or write the same files or communicate over pipes,
它们也可以读写相同的文件或通过管道进行通信，
but, in a sort of ordinary virtual machines, none of that's possible,
但是，在一种通常的虚拟机中，这些都是不可能的，
the different virtual machines running on the same computer
不同的虚拟机运行在同一台计算机上，
completely isolated from each other by the virtual machine monitors.
通过虚拟机监视器彼此完全隔离。
So people like them for security,
所以人们因为安全喜欢它们，
it's a way of being able to run untrusted software
这是一种能够运行不可信软件的方式，
without having to worry if it's buggy or malicious.
而不必担心它有漏洞或是恶意的。
You know in practice,
在实践中，
I've pitched the goal as being sort of completely faithful emulation of a physical machine,
我将目标定位为完全忠实地模拟物理机，
in fact, it turns out that for performance reasons, this is often blurred
事实上，由于性能原因，这通常是模糊的，
and you'll find for example that
比如，你会发现，
Linux and the most common virtual machine monitors have co-evolved a little bit,
Linux 和常见的虚拟机监视器有点协同发展，
so that in real life,
所以在现实生活中，
Linux may actually be aware that it's running on a virtual machine monitor
Linux 实际上可能意识到它是在虚拟机监视器上运行，
and with the virtual machine monitors permission for efficiency,
并且利用虚拟机监视的权限达到效率，
Linux sometimes knowingly talks down to the virtual machine monitors
Linux 有时会与虚拟机监视器交互，
to do things like get high-speed access to devices,
做一些事情，比如高速访问设备，
but that's a carefully controlled exception
但这是一个精心控制的例外情况，
and the general strategy is completely faithful simulation.
总体策略是完全忠实的模拟。
Okay, so how could we build our own virtual machine monitor.
好的，那么我们怎么才能建造我们自己的虚拟机监视器。
Well, one possibility would be to do it entirely in software,
好的，一种可能性是完全用软件来做，
you can imagine writing something like QEMU,
你可以想象写一些像 QEMU 这样的东西，
that interpreted the machine instructions,
它解释机器指令，
that is you could write a program that would open up the xv6
也就是说你可以编写一个程序来打开 xv6 ，
to read the file that has the xv6 instructions in it
读取包含 xv6 指令的文件，
and your program could look at these instructions,
你的程序可以查看这些指令，
say oh that's a load instruction or a move instruction
说，那是一条加载指令或一条移动指令，
and your program could you know sort of simulate RISC-V state,
你的程序可以模拟 RISC-V 状态，
may have 32 registers implemented in software,
可以有以软件实现的 32 个寄存器，
and as your software sort of reads each instruction and picks it apart,
当你的软件读取每条指令并将其拆分时，
it figures out what kind of instruction is,
它会弄清楚是什么指令，
it would apply the effects of that instruction to the 32 registers and control registers,
它会将指令应用于这 32 个寄存器和控制寄存器，
that it was simulating all in software.
这些寄存器都是用软件模拟的。
And people do this
人们这样做，
and it's conceptually straightforward to make it work,
理论上上很简单让它发挥作用，
although it maybe a lot of work to get all the details right,
尽管可能要做很多工作才能把所有的细节都做好，
the reason why sort of pure software interpretive virtual machines aren't widely used
纯软件解释型虚拟机之所以没有被广泛使用，
is that they're slow,
是因为它们速度慢，
if you play this game,
如果你这么做，
your virtual machine is going to run guest software
你的虚拟机将运行客户机软件
at a small fraction of the speed of the hardware that you're using,
以一个比你使用的硬件慢得多的速度运行，
because for every your virtual machine monitor software has to
因为你的虚拟机监控软件必须
look at every instruction as it's executed up here,
查看每条它要执行的指令，
your machine monitor is going to maybe run dozens of instructions
你的机器监视器可能运行数十条指令，
in the process of interpreting each one of the guest instructions
在解释每一条客户机指令的过程中，
and so it's going to be orders of magnitude slower than a real computer
所以它会比实际的计算机慢几个数量级，
and for something like cloud computing,
对于云计算之类的东西，
it really would not be a practical.
这是不现实的。
So people don't use the software interpretation
所以，人们不会使用软件解释
to build virtual machines for production systems,
来为生产系统构建虚拟机，
instead, sort of core of,
取而代之的是，某种核心的，
one of the main widely used strategies is
被广泛使用的主要策略之一是
to run the actually run the guest instructions on the real CPU.
在实际的 CPU 上运行客户机指令。
So if you were going to run xv6 in your virtual machine monitor,
所以，如果你要在虚拟机监视器中运行 xv6 ，
you would actually load xv6 its instructions the kernel,
你实际上会加载 xv6 内核的指令，
the beginning, you know entire xv6 instructions in a memory
一开始，内存中有完整的 xv6 指令，
and then jump to the first instruction in xv6, right.
然后跳到 xv6 中的第一条指令。
In order to have your computer actually run the instructions in xv6
为了让你的计算机实际运行 xv6 中的指令，
and of course this requires that your computer
当然，这需要你的计算机
has the same microprocessor in it that xv6 is expecting,
具有与 xv6 期望的相同的微处理器，
but that's easy to arrange.
但那很容易安排。
Now, it turns out you can't literally do this,
现在，事实证明你不能真的这么做，
point at which you run into trouble is
你会遇到麻烦的地方是，
when your guest operating system first executed a privileged instruction, right.
当你的客户机操作系统第一次执行特权指令时。
If, and you know that's really the difference between the kernel and ordinary user code is
内核和普通用户代码之间的真正区别是，
that kernels which is what we're trying to run here
我们试图在这里运行的内核，
in our virtual machine kernels use privileged instructions,
在虚拟机中，内核使用特权指令，
guest your guest kernel might for example
你的客户机内核，
try to load a new page table into the satp register RISC-V.
会尝试将新的页表加载到 RISC-V 的 satp 寄存器中。
So that's starting to present a puzzle,
所以这开始出现出一个难题，
if we're executing our guest kernel as an ordinary user process
如果我们将客户机内核作为普通用户进程运行，
and Linux for example boy loading satp an illegal instruction in user mode,
比如 Linux 在用户模式中加载 satp 是非法指令，
then so our programs going to crash,
那么我们的程序就会崩溃，
if we are so foolish as
如果我们愚蠢到
to load our guest kernel into and run it in supervisor mode,
将客户机内核加载并在管理模式下运行它，
somehow then our guest kernel will now be able to modify the real page table
有时候，我们的客户机内核将能够修改实际的页表，
and would be able to escape from its virtual machine,
将能够逃离它的虚拟机，
because it controls the contents of PTEs read and write any memory.
因为它可以控制 PTE 的内容，读写任何内存。
So we can't use a strategy that's as simple as
所以我们不能使用这种简单的策略，
just running the guest kernel directly,
只是直接运行客户机内核，
instead we're going to start playing some tricks.
相反，我们要使用一些技巧。
The first step is to run the guest kernel in user mode,
第一步，是在用户模式下运行客户机内核，
so, this is sort of the fundamental strategy here,
所以，这是一种基本策略，
what we're run the guest kernel in user mode,
我们在用户模式下运行客户机内核，
you know in RISC-V user mode
在 RISC-V 用户模式下，
and so what that means,
这意味着，
you know we're writing, we're writing our own virtual machine monitor
我们编写自己的虚拟机监视器，
and when we tell it look please boot xv6,
当我们告诉它启动 xv6 时，
it's going to load xv6's kernel instructions into memory somewhere,
它会将 xv6 的内核指令加载到内存中的某个地方，
maybe set up a page table appropriately,
或许设置一个页表，
that makes it look to xv6 like
这使得 xv6 中，
its memory starts at 0 and goes up to whatever high memory is,
它的内存从 0 开始到任何较高的内存，
and then the virtual machine monitor,
然后是虚拟机监视器，
we use a trap sret instruction as [evolved] come across on xv6
我们使用 xv6 上遇到的 trap sret 指令，
to jump into the first instruction of the guest OS in user mode,
在用户模式下，跳转到客户机操作系统的第一条指令，
so the guest operating system will execute along
所以，客户机操作系统将单独执行，
and many instructions will work fine,
很多指令都可以很好地工作，
if the guest operating systems just adding two registers together,
如果客户机操作系统将两个寄存器加在一起，
reading loading or storing from memory that'll just work
从内存中读取、加载或存储就可以了，
and as soon as the guest operating system uses privilege instruction,
并且一旦客户机操作系统使用特权指令，
what's gonna happen is it's going to trap,
接下来会发生的是它会 trap ，
the RISC-V hardware cause it,
RISC-V 硬件引起它，
since it's running in user mode, not supervisor mode,
由于它在用户模式下运行，而不是在管理者模式，
will cause it to trap back into the our virtual machine monitor
会导致它 trap 回到我们的虚拟机监视器，
and will get control,
我们将获得控制权，
so if the guest operating system, for example tries to change satp, the page table pointer,
所以如果客户操作系统试图修改 satp 页表指针，
boom, the RISC-V CPU will trap into our virtual machine monitor
RISC-V CPU 将 trap 进入我们的虚拟机监视器，
and our software will get control back.
我们的软件就会夺回控制权。
And our software we're able to look and see
而我们的软件能够查看
what instruction caused the trap and do something appropriate,
什么指令导致了 trap ，并采取适当的措施，
but the cool thing here is that,
但这里最酷的是，
the guest operating system didn't actually get to set the page table pointer.
客户及操作系统实际上并没有设置页表指针。
But how does how does the VMM intercept this,
但是 VMM 是如何拦截这个，
like it has to set the trap handler, right,
它必须设置 trap 处理程序，对吗，
isn't that something only a privileged process can do,
这不是只有特权进程才能做的事情吗，
VMM is a user program on the host OS right.
VMM 只是主机操作系统上的用户程序，对吧。
Okay, what I'm assuming,
好的，我假设，
what I'm assuming is that the virtual machine monitor runs in supervisor mode,
我假设虚拟机监视器在管理者模式下运行，
so in this simple picture,
所以，在这个简单的图中，
the virtual machine monitor is the kernel that boots on this piece of hardware,
虚拟机监视器是在这块硬件上启动的内核，
so instead of booting Linux or whatever you would boot this virtual machine monitor,
所以，不是启动 Linux ，而是你要启动的虚拟机监视器，
it boots in supervisor mode,
它在管理模式下启动，
it has complete control over the hardware,
它完全控制硬件，
so we can set up you know stvec and all this other stuff, however it likes.
所以我们可以设置 stvec 和所有其他东西。
That makes sense.
理解了。
You know, and actually some virtual machine monitors work exactly that way,
实际上有些虚拟机监视器就是这样工作的，
you just boot them on the hardware
你只需在硬件上启动它们，
and its just the virtual machine monitor only that's running in supervisor mode.
只有虚拟机监视器在管理程序模式下运行。
In fact, there's also many many virtual machines schemes out there,
事实上，还有很多虚拟机方案，
in fact, boot Linux,
事实上，启动 Linux ，
and then once Linux is up and running,
然后一旦 Linux 启动并运行，
you load, load the virtual
你加载虚拟的，
actually Linux, actually Linux comes with a virtual machine monitor,
实际上 Linux 带有一个虚拟机监视器，
or you load the virtual machine monitor
你加载虚拟机监视器，
as what's called loadable kernel module into Linux
所谓的可加载内核模块加载到 Linux 中，
and it runs in the kernel in supervisor mode.
并且它以管理者模式在内核中运行。
And that's the way actually today's paper says,
这就是今天的文件所说的方式，
boot Linux, then run this little loadable kernel module,
启动 Linux ，然后运行这个可加载的内核模块，
but the main point is the virtual machine monitor software
但重点是虚拟机监控软件，
and the software rewriting that we trust runs in supervisor mode,
我们重写的信任的软件运行管理者模式下，
now we're going to run the guest in user mode,
现在，我们可以在用户模式下运行客户机，
but arrange for it to look like it's running in supervisor mode as far as it's concerned.
但是要安排它看起来像是在管理者模式下运行。
Okay, so the good news is that
好的，好消息是，
on RISC-V, everything dangerous traps,
在 RISC-V 上，所有危险的 trap ，
if you try to do it in user mode,
如果你尝试在用户模式下执行此操作，
that is all the sort of privilege things that supervisor mode can do
这就是管理者模式可以执行的所有特权操作，
with with the exception of stuff having to do with the page table or PTE
除了与页表或 PTE 有关的内容，
which we'll talk about in a bit,
我们将在稍后讨论，
but basically every every supervisor only instruction causes a trap,
但每个管理者专用指令都会导致 trap ，
if you try to execute in user mode.
如果你尝试在用户模式下执行。
So that means that every time they gotta stop running system,
这意味着每次他们必须停止运行系统，
does anything like reads scause or reads writes stvec or does any of those things,
执行读取 scause 或读写 stvec 或执行任何这些操作，
that xv6 for example does to configure with the privileged part of RISC-V hardware
xv6 用于配置 RISC-V 硬件的特权部分，
will cause a trap into the virtual machine monitor
将导致 trap 进入虚拟机监视器，
and we'll get control.
我们将获得控制权。
And then, the game is going to be
然后，游戏将成为
the virtual machine monitor is going to maintain virtual state,
虚拟机监视器将会维护虚拟状态，
a whole table of virtual state information for for the guest,
客户机的虚拟状态信息的整个表，
so the virtual machine monitor will have,
所以虚拟机监视器将具有，
for example and virtual stvec register just implemented, that's a variable in software
比如，在软件中实现的虚拟 stvec 寄存器，
and a virtual sepc register
以及虚拟 sepc 寄存器，
and all these for all these protected registers,
所有这些受保护的寄存器，
there's a whole array of them down here,
这里有一整组的寄存器，
implemented by the virtual machine monitor
由虚拟机监视器实现，
and when the guest operating system for example runs the instruction,
当客户机操作系统运行指令时，
that reads one of these registers,
它读取这些寄存器中的一个，
boom it'll take a trap, because it's illegal in user space,
它会设 trap ，因为这在用户空间是不合法的，
the virtual machine monitor will inspect the instruction
虚拟机监视器将检查指令，
and say aha, that's an instruction that's reading the sepc register,
并说，这是一条指令读取 sepc 寄存器，
and so the virtual machine monitor will then emulate that instruction,
所以虚拟机监视器随后将模拟这个指令，
it will read the sepc virtual sepc value out of this array,
它将从数组中读取虚拟 sepc 的值，
it'll copy that into the hardware,
它会将其复制到硬件中，
well, what really happened here is that the,
好的，这里真正发生的事情是，
um, I forget the name of the,
嗯，我忘了它的名字，
there's some instruction whose name I forget,
有一条指令，我忘了它的名字，
which is basically ssread,
它是 ssread ，
although that's not its name
虽然这不是它的名字，
and you give it the name of an ordinary register
你给它一个普通的寄存器，
and the name of a privilege register like sepc
以及一个特权寄存器，比如 sepc ，
and so what the virtual, trap the virtual machine monitor will read that instruction,
所以 trap 虚拟机监视器将读取这个指令，
will see, oh, it's an ssread,
看到这是一个 ssread ，
virtual machine monitor will copy the virtual copy of sepc into a0 in the trapframe,
虚拟机监视器将复制虚拟 sepc 到 trapframe 的 a0 中，
after all when entering the VMM,
最后，当进入 VMM 时，
that's gonna have created a trapframe,
会创建一个 trapframe ，
copies of all the guests registers,
复制所有客户机寄存器，
that will copy this sepc into a0 in the trapframe,
复制 sepc 到 trapframe 中的 a0 ，
then return from the trap using sret,
然后使用 sret 从 trap 返回，
you know, after copying the trapframe registers, the real registers
在复制 trapframe 寄存器之后，真正的寄存器，
and return from this trap to the instruction after the ssread
从 trap 返回到 ssread 指令之后，
and continue reading there
并且继续在那里读取，
with now as a0 set to the virtual sepc.
将 a0 设置为虚拟 sepc 。
Now the guest operating system will proceed,
现在客户机操作系统将继续运行，
you know [] not realizing that something funny happened here,
[]没有意识到这里发生了一些有趣的事情，
but it will have gotten a copy of the virtual sepc
但它将获得虚拟 sepc 的复制，
that the VMM was keeping on its behalf.
保存在 VMM 之中。
So any questions about this, about this strategy?
那么对这个策略，有什么问题吗？
How does the VMM differentiate between different guests?
VMM 如何区分不同的客户机？
It, it, it's basically the same way,
它基本上是一样的，
it would keep one of these tables of virtual state per guest
它将为每个客户机保存一个虚拟状态表，
and it just knows just like xv6 knows which process is running
就像 xv6 知道哪个进程正在运行一样，
as a variable, maybe a per core variable saying,
有一个变量，可能是每个核心的变量表示，
here's the process I'm currently running,
这是我正在运行的进程，
similarly, a VMM would have a per core variable
类似地， VMM 将有每个核心的变量，
that indicated which virtual machine it will be multiple of these state structures,
它指示哪个虚拟机是这些状态结构，
VMM would know which virtual machine was executing
VMM 将知道哪个虚拟机正在运行，
and would look in the appropriate virtual machine state structure,
并且在适当的虚拟机状态结构中查找，
to find st, sepc or whatever it is looking for.
查找 sepc 或它正在寻找的任何东西。
Can it run multiple, can it assign multiple cores to one of the guests?
它可以为一个客户机分配多个核心吗？
Yes, sophisticated virtual machine monitors can do that, yes.
是的，先进的虚拟机监视器可以做到这一点，是的。
So if you, sorry, go ahead.
所以，如果你，抱歉，请继续。
Oh, sorry so the guest operating system,
哦，抱歉，所以客户机操作系统，
it will have like some registers,
它会有一些寄存器，
in the actual hardware will be the registers that the guest OS uses,
在实际硬件中是客户操作系统使用的寄存器，
so why do we not use the actual sepc, but use a virtual one?
那么为什么我们不使用实际的 sepc ，而使用虚拟的？
The reason is that the virtual machine monitor needs to use these registers,
原因是虚拟机监视器需要使用这些寄存器，
needs to use the real registers,
需要使用真实寄存器，
so for example think about scause,
比如，考虑一下 scause ，
when a trap occurs, what happens on,
当 trap 发生时，会发生什么，
when you know when the guest operating system tries to do anything privilege,
当客户机操作系统尝试执行任何特权时，
the trap will occur
将会发生 trap ，
and the hardware sets the real hardware scause register to the cause of the trap,
而硬件设置真实的 scause 寄存器为 trap 的原因，
which is illegal instruction or unprivileged instruction whatever it is,
不管是非法指令还是非特权指令，
but if the guest operating system,
但是如果客户机操作系统，
you know supposing the guest operating system
假设客户操作系统
has just taken a system call from a guest user process,
刚刚接受了来自客户用户进程的系统调用，
the guest operating system needs to see an scause,
客户机操作系统需要查看 scause ，
that's whatever the right scause value is for system call, right,
这才是系统调用的正确 scause 的值，
even though maybe the last thing that
即使可能最后一件事，
you know, so the the guest operating system is going to read scause,
客户机操作系统将读取 scause ，
you know in the trap handler
在 trap 处理程序中，
and what it thinks is
并且它认为，
the trap handler handling a system call from one of its guest processes,
trap 处理程序处理来自其客户机进程的系统调用，
the scause, that the guest operating system needs to see
客户操作系统需要查看的 scause ，
is the value that says that means system call,
那个值是不是系统调用，
but the scause is going to be,
但 scause 将会是，
the real scause register is the scause,
真正的 scause 寄存器是那个 scause ，
that means illegal instruction or unprivileged,
意味着非法指令或非特权指令，
or you know instructions violating the privilege rules,
或者违反特权规则的指令，
so, there are actually some times when you could,
所以，有些时候你可以，
well, anyway, in general the VMM, the VMM is the one that needs to see the real,
不管怎么说，一般说来， VMM 是需要看到真实的，
VMM needs to see different values in the real registers,
VMM 需要在真实寄存器中看到不同的值，
then the operating system should see it in its version of the registers.
而操作系统应该在它的寄存器中看到它。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
Thank you, yeah.
谢谢，是的。
Okay, so this is called,
好的，这就是所谓的，
the name for this style of a virtual machine implementation
这种风格的虚拟机实现的名称，
in which the guest runs at user level
客户机在用户级别运行，
and therefore traps whenever tries to do anything privileged
每当试图做任何有特权的事情时，都会进入 trap ，
and the VMM can emulate the privileged instruction
然后 VMM 可以模拟特权指令，
and the name for that is TRAP-AND-EMULATEE.
它的名字叫 TRAP-AND-EMULATE 。
And, it's nice,
而且，它很好，
because you can, you can build this for yourself,
因为你可以自己建造这个，
actually you can build this for yourselves entirely in software,
实际上，你们完全可以用软件为自己建造这个，
and you could modify xv6 for example to be a virtual machine monitor on RISC-V,
比如，你可以将 xv6 修改为 RISC-V 上的虚拟机监视器，
run over virtual machines, perhaps regular xv6,
运行虚拟机，也许是普通的 xv6 ，
just by writing software or software does have to run in supervisor mode.
只需编写在管理者模式下运行的软件。
The state here, all the registers that begin with s,
这里的状态，所有以 s 开头的寄存器，
all those supervisor control registers have to be part of this virtual state,
所有那些管理程序控制寄存器必须是虚拟状态的一部分，
there's also some other things that are not directly accessible,
还有一些其他的东西是不能直接接触到的，
from those s registers that nevertheless need to be down in this state,
那些不需要在这个状态下 s 寄存器，
one of them is the mode,
其中之一是模式，
the virtual machine monitor needs to know
虚拟机监视器需要知道，
whether the virtual machines running in a guest user mode or guest operating system,
虚拟机运行在客户用户模式还是客户操作系统中，
because for example if if user code executes the privileged instruction
因为比如如果用户代码执行特权指令，
like trying to read scause,
比如，尝试读取 scause ，
sure that'll cause a trap into the VMM too,
当然这也会导致 trap 进入 VMM ，
but in that case, the VMM should not just emulate the instruction in return,
但是在这种情况下， VMM 不应该仅仅模拟指令，
because that's not a legal instruction in user mode,
因为这不是用户模式下的合法指令，
so the VMM has to track
所以， VMM 必须跟踪
whether the guest is in guest supervisor mode or guest user mode
客户机是处于客户机管理者模式还是客户机用户模式，
and so there's going to be a mode slot down here as well
所以这里也会有一个模式插槽，
and the VMM will know,
VMM 就会知道，
because when the guest operating system jumps into a user space,
因为当客户机操作系统跳入用户空间时，
it'll execute the sret instruction,
它将执行 sret 指令，
sret is a privilege instruction,
sret 是一条特权指令，
so the VMM will actually get control there
所以， VMM 将在那里获得控制权，
and will see, oh the guest is running an sret instruction,
然后就会发现客户机正在运行一条 sret 指令，
among other things I'm gonna change the virtual mode from supervisor to user.
在其他方面，我将把虚拟机模式从管理者改为用户。
And another hidden piece of state is the hart number, that is the core number,
另一个隐藏的状态是 hart 数，也就是核心数，
you can't get that directly even with the privileged instruction,
即使有了特权指令，你也不能直接访问它，
but the VMM manager needs to keep track of which hart it's emulating right now.
但是 VMM 管理器需要跟踪它现在正在模拟的 hart 。
Okay, the RISC-V it turns out different CPUs are different levels of difficulty,
好的， RISC-V 证明不同的 CPU 有不同的难度，
how hard it is to write a trap-and-emulate virtual machine on the RISC-V,
在 RISC-V 上编写 trap-and-emulate 虚拟机是多么困难，
particularly well suited to it,
特别是适应它，
because the designers had that in mind
因为设计者必须考虑这些，
when they were designing the instruction set
在他们设计指令集时，
and so they knew what the requirements of a trap-and-emulate virtual machine were,
所以，他们知道 trap-and-emulate 虚拟机的要求是什么，
and for example, they've been quite diligent in making sure that
比如，他们非常努力地确保，
every single privilege thing that supervisor code can do will cause a trap,
管理者代码可以执行的每一项特权操作会导致 trap ，
if you try to do it in user mode,
如果你尝试在用户模式下执行它，
which is what you need,
这是你需要的，
in order to make sure the virtual machine monitor sees a trap for every privileged instructions.
确保虚拟机监视器看到每个特权指令的 trap 。
I have a quick question,
我有一个简短的问题，
so does anything actually run in the guest OS itself
那么，是否有任何运行在客户机操作系统本身中的，
or does it always trap into the virtual machine monitor?
或者它总是 trap 进入虚拟机监视器中？
All ordinary instructions,
所有普通指令，
like if you just have an add instruction,
比如如果你只有一条加法指令，
that you know adds, I don't know how to write this RISC-V assembly,
add ，我不知道这个用 RISC-V 汇编怎么写，
but let's just say you add a0 to a1
但是假设你把 a0 加到 a1 上，
and you want to put the result in a2,
你想把结果放到 a2 里，
that instruction just executes directly on the hardware at full hardware speed.
这个指令直接在硬件上执行，以全部硬件数度。
If you make a function call, just an ordinary function call,
如果你使用一个普通的函数调用，
up here in the guest world,
在客户机世界里，
that just executes without anything special, just a ordinary,
它只是执行，没有什么特殊的，只是一个普通的，
you know all the instructions that are legal in user code,
所有指令在用户代码中都是合法的，
[] these instructions just execute directly at full speed
这些指令以全速直接执行，
when the guest operating system executes them.
当客户机执行它们的时候。
Okay, so is there a [semblance] of like user mode and kernel mode in the guest OS.
好的，那么在客户机操作系统中有没有用户模式和内核模式的[外观]呢？
Yes, the guest operating system is,
是的，客户机操作系统是，
well, the guest operating system is unchanged,
客户机操作系统没有改变，
so what we're running up here is exactly the Linux kernel,
我们在这里运行的就是 Linux 内核，
are exactly the xv6 kernel
就是 xv6 内核，
and of course xv6 all you know it knows the,
当然， xv6 知道，
xv6 kernel knows it's running in supervisor mode, right,
xv6 内核知道它在管理模式下运行，
just just is of course it's not here,
当然它不在这里，
but as far as the code is concerned,
但就代码而言，
it's just definitely running in supervisor mode,
它肯定是在运行管理模式，
it just does all kinds of privilege things and expects them to work,
它做各种特权的事情，并期望它们能起作用，
and then it knows when it executes sret to get into user space
然后它知道何时执行 sret 进入用户空间，
and knows aha, I'm gonna enter user space now.
知道现在要进入用户空间了。
And you know the VMM sort of makes everything look like
VMM 让一切看起来都像是
that's indeed what's happening,
这些真的在发生，
even though it's actually in in in in the real machine,
即使它是在真实的机器里，
it's in user mode, in both places,
在这两个地方，它都处于用户模式，
but this looks just like supervisor mode,
但这看起来是管理者模式，
this looks just like user mode.
这看起来是用户模式。
Okay.
好的。
Okay, so when the, so for example when the guest
好的，当客户机，
when we execute sret to enter user space,
当我们执行 sret 进入用户空间时，
the sret privileged luckily traps into the virtual machine monitor,
sret 特权被幸运地捕获到虚拟机监视器中，
virtual machine monitor changes the virtual mode to user,
虚拟机监视器将虚拟模式更改为用户模式，
even though of course the real mode is still supervisor,
当然，真正的模式仍然是管理者模式，
because we're still going to be down here,
因为我们还在下面，
change the virtual mode to the user,
将虚拟模式改变为用户模式，
it just before it returns from the trap,
在它从 trap 返回之前，
the virtual machine monitor sets the real sepc to the virtual sepc,
虚拟机监视器将真实 sepc 设置为虚拟 sepc ，
because in order that when the virtual machine monitor returns using its own sret,
因为在虚拟机监视器使用自己的 sret 返回时，
that the the program counter value,
程序计数器值，
it returns to as a program value is
它作为程序值返回是
the program counter that the guest operating system wanted to return to.
客户操作系统想要返回的程序计数器。
So here's a case where very briefly
这里有一个非常简短的例子，
the real sepc was set equal to the virtual sepc,
真实的 sepc 被设置为虚拟的 sepc ，
and I'll talk about this in a bit,
稍后我会谈到这一点，
a virtual machine monitor also is going to be switching page tables,
虚拟机监视器也会切换页表，
when it goes back into, into the virtual machine,
当它返回到虚拟机时，
when the guest user code wants to make it,
当客户机用户代码想要，
then the guest user code for ordinary instructions execute machine,
客户机代码普通指令执行机器，
execute them directly at full speed,
以全速执行它们，
when the guest code wants to make a system call,
当客户机代码想要进行系统调用时，
executes the ecall instruction,
执行 ecall 指令，
that causes a trap,
这会导致 trap ，
that trap goes to the virtual machine monitor in this scheme,
这个 trap 会到达虚拟机监视器，
the virtual machine monitor says aha,
虚拟机监视器会说，
where in it [] the virtual mode, its virtual mode is user space,
它的虚拟模式是用户空间，
it looks at the instruction,
它会查看指令，
the trap that faulted its ecall,
trap 导致 ecall ，
and then the virtual machine monitor,
然后虚拟机监视器
sort of does all the virtual changes makes all the changes in the virtual state required
修改所有需要修改的虚拟状态，
to simulate a system call trap into the guest operating system,
模拟系统调用 trap 到客户机操作系统中，
so it's going to set the virtual sepc to be whatever program counter,
所以它会将虚拟 sepc 设置为程序计数器，
was the ecall instruction was that going to change the virtual mode back to supervisor,
ecall 指令将虚拟模式改回管理者模式，
it's gonna set the virtual scause to be system call,
它会将虚拟 scause 设置为系统调用，
it's gonna set the real epc to be equal to the virtual stvec,
它会将真实的 ecp 设置为虚拟的 stvec ，
and then call sret,
然后调用 sret ，
so that all jump into the guest operating systems trap handler,
从而完全跳转到客户机操作系统 trap 处理程序，
which is what or trampoline page or whatever it is
或者是 trampoline 还是别的什么，
which is what the virtual stvec was pointing to.
这就是虚拟 stvec 所指向的。
Okay.
好的。
We have two remaining pieces of business which are quite important,
我们还有两个非常重要的东西，
one is, what about page tables,
一个是，关于页表，
and the other is, what about devices.
另一个是，关于设备。
So the page table sort of there's two pieces to that,
页表，这里有两个部分，
one is that at various points,
其一是在不同的时间点，
the guest operating system is going to modify the satp register
客户机操作系统将修改 satp 寄存器，
and of course you know that they'll turn into a trap at the virtual machine monitor
当然，它们会变成虚拟机监视器的 trap ，
and the virtual machine monitor gets a chance to do something,
虚拟机监视器获得了做事的机会，
but what we don't want the virtual machine monitor to do is
但是我们不希望虚拟机监视器做的是，
simply let the guest set the real satp,
简单地让客户机设置真正的 satp ，
and then execute after having changed the real satp,
然后在改变了真实的 satp 之后执行，
because that would let the guest get at any memory,
因为这会让客户机得到任何内存，
not just the memory that the virtual machine monitor has allocated to it,
不仅是虚拟机监视器分配给它的内存，
so we cannot let the guest operating system simply set the satp,
所以，我们不能让客户机操作系统简单地设置 satp ，
but we do need to do something to the satp,
但我们确实需要对 satp 做点什么，
because we need to provide the illusion to the guest operating system,
因为我们需要向客户操作系统提供某种幻觉，
that yes, indeed, the page tables can change
是的，页表可以更改，
and more than an illusion,
并且不仅仅是错觉，
when the guest software runs load and store instructions or fetches instructions to execute,
当客户机软件运行加载和存储指令或取出指令来执行时，
we need those to come from the right place,
我们需要这些东西来自正确的地方，
from the place that the guest operating system pointed its page table entries too,
从客户机操作系统指向其页表条目的位置，
so what actually happens when the guest sets the satp,
那么当客户机设置 satp 时到底会发生什么，
is, we you know we we can't,
你知道我们不能，
we can't directly use the guest operating systems page table,
我们不能直接使用客户机操作系统页表，
but the virtual machine monitor cooks up a new page table,
但是虚拟机监视器创建一个新的页表，
that simulates the guest operating systems desired page table,
用来模拟客户操作系统所需的页表，
so, the, so now the page translation situation is a little bit different,
所以现在页面转换的情况有点不一样，
we have the guest,
我们有客户机，
with the guest was trying to set the page table too,
客户机试着设置页表，
so this is the guest page table,
所以这是客户机页表，
of course is the kernel guest kernel,
当然是客户机内核，
and that maps sort of guest virtual addresses to what I'll call guest physical addresses,
它将客户机虚拟地址映射到客户机物理地址，
of course the guest physical addresses are
当然，客户机物理地址是
the virtual machine monitor given the guest 32 gigabytes or however much,
虚拟机监视器给客户机的 32GB 或其他大小，
simulate physical memory for its use,
模拟物理内存以供其使用，
presumably starting at, telling the guest operating system that
告诉客户机操作系统，
its physical addresses start at 0 and go up for 32 megabytes,
它的物理地址从 0 开始到 32MB ，
but of course you know they don't in real life on the real hardware,
当然，它们不是在真实的硬件上，
there are just 32 gigabytes of pages somewhere not contiguous,
有 32GB 的页面，但不是连续的，
can't use, can't directly use the guest's physical addresses,
不能直接使用客户机物理地址，
because they don't correspond to real physical addresses,
因为它们并不对应真实的物理地址，
so instead the VMM is going to maintain a map for each virtual machine,
相反， VMM 将为每个虚拟机维护一个映射，
that maps guest physical addresses to real physical addresses,
将客户机物理地址映射到实际物理地址，
what I call host physical addresses,
我将它称为主机物理地址，
so this map is like a page table
这个映射就像是一个页表，
has an entry for every page,
有每个页面的条目，
every physical page the guests thinks exists
客户机认为存在的每个物理页面，
and indicates what real physical page that guest physical address refers to
并指示客户机物理地址关联的实际物理页面，
that the VMM is allocated for it,
由 VMM 为其分配的，
and then, when the guest writes a new page table to satp,
然后，当客户机将新页表写入 satp 时，
in the trap handler, for that VMM creates what's called a shadow page table,
在 trap 处理程序中， VMM 创建所谓的影子页表，
which is going to be what the VMM puts in the real satp,
这是 VMM 在真正的 satp 中放入的内容，
and this shadow page table is constructed by the combination of these two page tables
这个影子页表由这两个页表的组合构成，
and so it maps guest virtual addresses to host physical addresses,
所以它将客户机虚拟地址映射到主机物理地址，
then is constructed by taking every entry in the guest page table,
然后通过取得客户机页表中的每个条目，
looking at the guest desired guest physical address,
查看期望的客户机物理地址，
using the VMM map to translate that guest physical address to a real host physical address
使用 VMM 映射将客户机物理地址转换为实际主机物理地址，
and putting that virtual physical pair into the shadow page table
将虚拟物理对放入影子页表中，
and then the virtual machine monitor sets this to be in satp as the real page table,
然后虚拟机监视器将这个设置为 satp 作为真实页表，
before returning back to the guest kernel,
在返回到客户内核之前，
so the guest kernel thinks it's one page table,
所以客户机内核认为它是一个页表，
but actually the real hardware is using this shadow page table instead.
但实际上真正的硬件使用的是这个影子页表。
And this way there's the,
这样一来，
this is what prevents the guest from escaping from the memory it's allowed to use,
这防止客户机从允许使用的内存中逃脱，
the the the shadow page table can only contain host physical addresses,
影子页表只能包含主机物理地址，
that the VMM had allocated for that guest,
VMM 为那个客户机分配的，
guest theres nothing that guest can put in the page table,
客户机没有什么可以放在页表中，
asks for that allow it to access a page
允许它访问页面，
that wasn't allocated to it by the virtual machine monitor.
虚拟机监视器没有分配给它的页面。
That's a critical piece of those isolation story here,
这是这些隔离故事中的一个关键部分，
any questions about the paging setup for trap-and-emulate?
关于 trap-and-emulate 的页面设置，有什么问题吗？
Sorry, so if it's if the operating system,
抱歉，如果操作系统，
the guest just wants to make a new, a new process,
客户机想要创建一个新的进程，
a new page table for the process,
一个进程的新的页表，
what does it do, what happens?
会发生什么？
The guest, the guest does, does the usual
客户机像平常一样做，
just does exactly what Linux or xv6 does right now,
只是做 Linux 或 xv6 做的事情，
formats up a page table entries to make a page table
格式化页表条目以生成页表，
and then it executes the instruction
然后它执行执行，
to assign that address of the page table into satp,
将页表的地址分配给 satp ，
so that's what the guest operating system does.
这就是客户机操作系统所做的。
And when the, but it can't actually assign the satp,
但它不能实际分配 satp ，
because that's a privileged operation,
因为这是一个特权操作，
so there's a trap into the virtual machine monitor,
所以在虚拟机监视器中有一个 trap ，
the virtual machine monitor inspects the instruction in trap,
虚拟机监视器在 trap 中检查指令，
sees oh gosh that guest is trying to assign to satp,
看到客户机正试图分配给 satp ，
and then the virtual machine monitor would create this new shadow page table
然后虚拟机监视器将创建新的影子页表，
from the combination of the page table the guest ask, was trying to set up,
根据客户机想要设置的页表的组合，
the virtual machine monitor looks at the page table
虚拟机监视器查看页表，
all the PTEs in the page table the guests was trying to set up,
客户机试图设置的页表中的所有 PTE ，
it runs it translates the physical address in each guest page table entry
它转换每个客户机页表条目中的物理地址，
through this map to get a real physical address or to cause a real fault,
通过这个映射获得真实的物理地址或导致真实的错误，
if the guest is trying to use a physical address that is not allowed to
如果客户机尝试使用不允许的物理地址，
and then the virtual machine monitor installs this shadow page table at the real satp
然后虚拟机监视器在真正的 satp 安装这个影子页表，
and returns back to the guest.
并返回给客户。
Oh, okay, okay I see, I see,
哦，好的，好的，我明白了，
okay, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
Yes.
好的。
Okay, so this this shadow page table stuff is certainly one of the tricky aspects
好的，这个影子页表是一个棘手的方面，
implementing a virtual machine monitor.
实现虚拟机监视器。
There's actually another thing that,
还有另一件事，
there's another way in which the guest operating system can interact with the page table,
客户操作系统可以通过另一种方式与页表交互，
the guest operating system may actually,
客户机操作系统可能会，
you know xv6 sometimes directly reads and writes page table entries in its page table,
xv6 有时会在页表中直接读写页表项，
and you know so xv6 could can modify page table entry
xv6 可以修改页表条目，
or read the dirty bits, for example in a page table entry,
或者读取页表条目中的脏位，
you know on the RISC-V, if, if a software modifies the page table entry,
在 RISC-V 上，如果软件修改了页表条目，
if you read the RISC-V spec,
如果你读过 RISC-V 规范，
RISC-V is not required to do anything at that point,
RISC-V 在这一点上不需要做任何事情，
so if you modify a page table entry,
所以，如果你修改页表条目，
the RISC-V microprocessor does not promise
RISC-V 微处理器不承诺
to immediately observe that modification to a page table entry,
立即观察对页表条目修改，
it may completely ignore it for the time being,
它可能会暂时完全忽略它，
instead what the manual says is,
相反，手册所说的是，
that if if you modify page table entries
如果你修改页表条目，
and you actually want the hardware MMU to see them,
你想让硬件 MMU 看到它们，
you have to execute, the sfence.vma instruction
你必须执行 sfence.vma 指令，
and the specs has only this instruction
而且规范只有这条指令，
that causes the hardware to pay attention to your page table modifications.
可以让硬件注意你对页表的修改。
And so if you're building a virtual machine monitor,
所以，如果你正在构建虚拟机监视器，
the virtual machine monitor on RISC-V
RISC-V 上的虚拟机监视器
can completely ignore the guest modifications to page table entries,
可以完全忽略客户机对页表条目的修改，
but since you know the guest is going to issue,
但是由于客户机会执行，
is going to execute an sfence.vma instruction after modifying page table entries,
在修改页表条目之后执行 sfence.vma 指令，
and this is a privileged instruction,
这是一条特权指令，
you can tell because it starts with s,
因为它以 s 开头，
that's going to trap into the virtual machine monitor,
这将 trap 进入虚拟机监视器，
virtual machine monitor is gonna [] knows that an sfence was executed,
虚拟机监视器将知道 sfence 被执行，
it looks the instruction,
它查看这条指令，
it's gonna re-scan the guest, the guest version of the current page table, current page table
它将重新扫描客户机的当前页表，
and look for page table entries that have changed
查找已经改变的页表条目，
and reflect those changes if they're legal into the shadow page table,
并且如果这些改变是合法的，则将它们反映到影子页表中，
reset the,
重新设置，
actually got a real sfence.vma
得到了一个真正的 sfence.vma ，
to get the real hardware to pay attention to the shadow page table,
让真正的硬件关注影子页表，
then return to the guest operating system.
然后返回到客户机操作系统。
So this means that,
所以这意味着，
there's only like the MMU actually just uses one page table, right,
MMU 实际上只使用了一个页表，对吧，
which is the shadow,
就是影子页表，
it's not like it's using the EPT or anything like that.
它没有在使用 EPT 或类似的东西。
There's no EPT yet.
现在还没有 EPT 。
Okay, so the guest just thinks it has a page table like the gva to gpa,
好的，所以客户机认为它有一个 gva 到 gpa 的页表，
but that's not actually doing any translation in the VMM,
但并不在 VMM 中进行任何转换，
yeah, makes its own page table based on both of them combined.
基于两者的结合制作自己的页表。
That's right, that's right,
是的，
just to be clear the EPT is part of a different,
需要说明的是， EPT 是不同的，
quite different virtual machine implementation,
完全不同的虚拟机实现，
virtual machine design that requires hardware support,
需要硬件支持的虚拟机设计，
assuming this is a story about
假设这是一个故事，
how to build a virtual machine with no special hardware support
如何在没有特殊硬件支持的情况下构建虚拟机，
other than trapping on privileged instructions.
而是使用 trap 特权指令。
Does this mess up direct mapping in anyway?
这有没有弄乱直接映射？
Well, there won't be a direct map,
好的，不会有直接映射，
this will allow the guest,
这允许客户机，
I mean, this will cause the guest kernel to run correctly,
我的意思是，这里客户机内核会正确运行，
with what the guest kernel thinks is the direct mapping,
客户机内核认为是直接映射，
but it's a direct, a direct mapping in the virtual world,
但它是虚拟世界的直接映射，
but it's not a direct mapping on the, on the real machine.
但不是真实机器上的直接映射。
But it doesn't matter,
但这无关紧要，
because, because we're tricking, yeah we're tricking the guests,
因为，因为我们在对客户机耍花招
everything looks just like it was a direct mapping.
一切看起来都像是直接映射。
Oh, one more question,
哦，还有一个问题，
you may be addressing this later,
你稍后可能会解决这个问题，
but I wonder like when we discussed the trap mechanism earlier
但我想知道我们之前讨论 trap 机制的时候，
and this must we mentioned the high performance cost to trapping,
我们提到了 trap 的高性能成本，
but this sounds like there's way more of performance [] when we use the VMM.
但听起来我们使用 VMM 的性能要高得多。
Yes, yes, there's all these instructions,
是的，是的，这里有所有的指令，
you know if you if your operating system may excuse a lot of privilege instructions, which may
如果你的操作系统执行很多特权指令，
and you spend a lot of time in the operating system,
而且你花了很多时间在操作系统上，
then the traps you may have quite a few traps,
你可能有相当多的 trap ，
that may cost you quite a bit of performance
这可能会耗费相当多的性能，
and that's what motivates
这就是我们的动机，
and a little bit we'll talk about modern hardware support virtual machines,
我们会稍微讨论一下现代硬件对虚拟机的支持，
which is what today's paper was using
这就是今天的论文所使用的，
and there high cost of the traps is a lot of the motivation
高昂的 trap 成本是很大的动机，
for why Intel felt compelled to and AMD felt compelled to add hardware support
为什么 Intel 和 AMD 觉得有必要增加硬件支持，
for a much more efficient,
以实现更高效率，
or for virtual machine scheme that had much many fewer traps.
或者用少得多的 trap 的虚拟机方案。
Yes, that's quite important,
是的，这很重要，
but this actually ran,
但这实际上运行，
I mean for many years, this is what people did for virtual machines
我的意思是，很多年来，这就是人们对虚拟机所做的，
and it was very successful, and it works
它非常成功，而且很管用，
and it's so much slower,
它慢得多，
but not so much slower that people didn't like it,
但不是慢到人们不喜欢它，
people like it a lot.
人们非常喜欢它。
Okay, any more questions about the trap-and-emulate strategy for page tables?
好的，关于页表的 trap-and-emulate 策略，还有什么问题吗？
Okay, let me, final a piece of the trap-and-emulate story,
好的，最后一段 trap-and-emulate 的故事，
let me talk about devices.
让我来谈谈设备。
So here I'm talking about,
所以我在这里说的是，
you know ordinary operating system expects to be able to get a disk drive to storage file system on
普通的操作系统希望能够获得磁盘驱动来存储文件系统，
or maybe network interface card,
或者是网卡，
and maybe it's in xv6 UART,
或许是在 xv6 中的 UART ，
so we can talk to its console,
我们可以和它的控制台交互，
who knows, the sound card, graphics adapter, mouse, keyboard, all kinds of stuff,
还有声卡，图形适配器，鼠标，键盘，各种各样的东西，
so the operating system, we need to,
所以操作系统，我们需要，
a virtual machine scheme has to have some provision to allow allow guests,
虚拟机方案必须具有某些规定以允许客户机，
to at least trick them into thinking that all these devices that they need really exist.
至少欺骗让它们认为所有这些需要的设备都是真实存在的。
And there's three main strategies that people use.
人们使用的策略主要有三种。
One is just pick some very commonly used device in the classic that you need,
一种是挑选一些你需要的非常常用的设备，
say a disk drive and just do emulation,
比如磁盘驱动器，只需进行模拟，
that is, you're not actually having a real device,
也就是说，你实际上并没有拥有一个真正的设备，
that VMM just makes it look like this particular kind of disk drive exists
VMM 只是让它看起来这种特定的磁盘驱动器存在，
and that the guest is talking to it.
让客户机和它交互。
And the way you would drive this emulation,
驱动这种模拟的方式，
typically the guest operating system is gonna
通常客户操作系统将
try to talk to the device through memory mapped control registers,
通过内存映射控制寄存器与设备交互，
so this is how xv6 talks to, it's UA- UART
这就是 xv6 与 UART 的交互方式，
you know the serial port, the console device,
串行端口，控制台设备，
that you type characters to and that displays characters to you,
你可以键入字符，它向你显示字符，
xv6 talking to control registers that are mapped,
xv6 与映射的控制寄存器交互，
that assumes the hardware has mapped in a known address
假设硬件已经映射到已知地址，
in the address in the kernel's address space,
在内核地址空间的地址中，
and so the way you emulate that in a virtual machine monitor is
所以，你在虚拟机监视器中进行模拟的方式是
actually not map those pages in the guest,
不是映射这些页面到客户机，
instead you would allow or have those pages be invalid
相反，你应该让这些页面非法，
so that every time the guest operating system tried to use the UART hardware,
从而每次客户操作系统尝试使用 UART 硬件时，
whatever device hardware,
无论设备硬件是什么，
the VMM virtual machine monitor will get a trap
VMM 虚拟机监视器将获得 trap ，
and the virtual machine monitor will going to look at the instructions,
虚拟机监视器将查看指令，
oh, it's trying to send a character on the UART
哦，它试图在 UART 上发送一个字符，
or read from the disk or who knows what,
或者从磁盘读取，或者别的什么，
and the virtual machine monitor would have some simulation of a disk,
然后虚拟机监视器将模拟磁盘，
a simulation of a serial device,
模拟串行设备，
and you know sort of invoke its simulation
调用它的模拟
to figure out how to respond to the guest instruction
来解决如何响应客户机的指令，
and then allow the guest to resume.
然后让客户机继续。
And so this is basically
这基本上就是，
how QEMU implements the UART console device, that xv6 uses,
QEMU 如何实现 xv6 使用的 UART 控制台设备，
it just has, there's actually no physical serial port in side,
实际上没有物理的串行端口，
but QEMU emulates one to keep xv6 happy.
但是 QEMU 模仿了一个让 xv6 使用。
And so this is a common strategy,
所以这是一个普遍的策略，
it's can be very low performance though,
它的性能可能会非常低，
because it involves a trap and the operating system,
因为它涉及 trap 和操作系统，
for every interaction between the guest and the device hardware,
对于每次客户机和设备硬件之间的交互，
but for low speed stuff, it's works pretty well.
但是对于低速的东西，它工作得很好。
The second strategy that's often used,
第二种经常使用的策略，
and actually, but if your,
实际上，如果你的，
if your goal is to provide is to be able to boot operating systems,
如果你的目标是提供能够启动操作系统，
that have no idea they're running on a virtual machine,
它们不知道它们是在虚拟机上运行的，
this is pretty much the way you have to go,
这几乎就是你必须走的路，
there's really no other choice.
别无选择。
But in the modern world,
但在现代世界中，
you know, it's often the case that the operating systems are aware,
通常情况下，操作系统会意识到，
that they're actually running at a low level,
它们是在低水平运行，
at least aware that they're running on top of a virtual machine,
至少意识到它们是在虚拟机之上运行，
and so a different strategy is to provide virtual devices,
所以，一种不同的策略是提供虚拟设备，
that is not trying to emulate a real device,
这并不是试图模仿真实的设备，
but cook up a device interface that is particularly efficient for the,
而是设计一种特别有效的设备接口，
provides efficient ways for the device driver in the guest,
为客户中的设备驱动程序提供有效的方式，
to be able to talk to a device support inside the virtual machine monitor,
能够与虚拟机监视器内部的设备进行交互，
and so you might not have memory map control registers
所以，你可能没有内存映射控制寄存器，
and said you might have sort of a queue of command structures in memory,
你可能在内存中有一个命令结构的队列，
in which the guest operating system would write its commands to the, to the device,
客户机操作系统可以将命令写入到那个设备，
and in fact xv6 also uses one of these,
事实上， xv6 也使用了其中的一种，
if you look at the xv6 VIRTIO_DISK, virtio_disk.c,
如果你查看 xv6 VIRTIO_DISK virtio_disk.c ，
you'll see the guest and the device driver
你将看到客户机和设备驱动程序
intended to talk to a disk virtual device that's implemented by QEMU,
与 QEMU 实现的磁盘虚拟设备交互，
and it uses either little or almost not,
它使用很少或几乎不使用，
either little or no memory mapped control registers
很少或没有内存映射控制寄存器，
and so it doesn't really rely on traps,
所以它并不依赖于 trap ，
and instead it formats up this sort of queue of commands memory,
而是，格式化这种命令内存队列，
as I mentioned,
正如我提到的，
and then QEMU looks at these commands in memory
然后 QEMU 查看内存中的这些命令，
and applies them not to a real disk,
不将它们应用于真正的磁盘，
but to a file like for us fs.img,
而是到 fs.img 这样的文件，
QEMU applies commands to fs.img
QEMU 将命令应用到 fs.img ，
instead of, instead of using a real piece of device hardware,
而不是使用真正的设备硬件，
just another strategy.
这是另一种策略。
And the third strategy that people use,
人们使用的第三种策略，
so this is higher performance and straight emulation,
所以，这是更高的性能和直接的仿真，
because you can design the interface,
因为你可以设计接口，
so it doesn't require a lot of traps,
所以不需要很多 trap ，
a final strategy people use is pass through a real device,
人们使用的最后一种策略是通过真实的设备，
and that sort of classic situation for this network interface controllers,
对于网络接口控制器来说，这是一种典型的情况，
you know that provide access to the network,
它提供了对网络的访问，
and modern network devices actually have hardware support
现代网络设备具有硬件支持，
for talking to multiple guest operating systems
用于与多个客户机操作系统交互，
running under a virtual machine monitor,
运行在虚拟机器监视器上，
so you can configure a modern NIC
所以，你可以配置现代网卡，
to actually act as if it's multiple independent, apparently independent NICs,
像是多个独立网卡，
one for each guest operating system,
每个客户机操作系统对应一个，
and then the guest operating system can talk directly,
然后客户机操作系统可以直接交互，
can be configured by the virtual machine monitors,
可以由虚拟机监视器配置，
so that is allowed to talk directly to its sort of slice of the network interface card hardware,
允许它以直接与它的那一部分网卡交互，
with very high efficiency,
使用很高的效率，
so this is the modern high performance way.
这就是现代高性能的方式，
The guest operating system probably,
客户机操作系统可能，
in theory I think you could design,
从理论上讲，我认为你可以设计，
you could set this up to the guest operating system
你可以设置客户机操作系统，
wasn't really aware did anything odd was going on,
不知道发生什么奇怪的事情，
but I think in practice, the guest operating system device drivers kind of know,
但我认为在实践中，客户机操作系统设备驱动程序可能知道，
they're talking to one of these special network interface cards.
它们正在与一块特殊的网卡交互。
Alright, so, so these are the options for devices,
好的，这些是设备的选项，
in fact I I I believe that most of the difficulty
事实上，我相信大部分的困难
in implementing virtual machine monitor today,
在今天实现虚拟机监控时，
comes in the form of trying to cook up device emulation and device drivers
是试图创造设备模拟和设备驱动程序，
that are a sufficiently good,
它是足够好的，
that they'll actually work correctly with a real guest operating systems,
它们会在真正的客户操作系统上正常工作，
this is where probably the majority of the work is,
这可能是大部分的工作，
particularly if you need to use this emulation strategy.
特别是当你使用这个模拟策略时。
Any questions about devices?
关于设备，有什么问题吗？
Okay, what what exactly is I I didn't quite get the difference
好的，我不太明白它们之间的区别，
between the virtual and emulation,
虚拟和模拟之间的区别，
because they don't like they.
因为它们不是。
They're similar, they're similar,
它们是相似的，
the here's a way to think about it,
这是一种思考它的方式，
if you're booting an operating system that has no idea about virtual machine,
如果你在启动一个对虚拟机一无所知的操作系统，
it probably has a lot of disk drivers in it,
它可能有很多磁盘驱动程序，
but they're all for real hardware,
但它们都是针对真正的硬件的，
that you can go out physical chunks of hardware
你可以拿出实体的硬件，
that you can go out and buy,
你可以出去买，
and that means that
这意味着，
if you want to boot that kind of operating system on your virtual machine,
如果你想在你的虚拟机上启动这种操作系统，
you need to have a exact emulation,
你需要有一个精确的模拟，
you need to choose one of those real pieces of hardware
你需要从那些真正的硬件中选择一个，
and have a precise super accurate emulation of that hardware,
并对那个硬件进行精确的模拟，
so at the, and then,
所以，然后，
I mean people totally do that, so that works,
我的意思是，人们完全这样做，所以这是可行的，
however, and that would be fine, except most of these,
这是可用的，除了大多数，
for real hardware that the device interfaces were not design,
对于真正的硬件，设备接口不是设计好的，
the hardware interfaces were not designed
硬件接口设计没有设计为
to be efficient with a trap-and-emulate virtual machine monitor,
高效率的使用 trap-and-emulate 虚拟机监视器，
and so it's very often the case that,
所以，通常是这种情况，
the real devices requires you to read and write its control registers a lot,
真正的设备需要大量读写它的控制寄存器，
but the virtual machine monitor has to get control
但是虚拟机监视器必须控制
for every write of a device control register,
对每次设备控制寄存器的写入，
because it needs to emulate
因为它需要模仿，
and that means that every write of a device control register
这意味着设备控制寄存器的每一次写入
results in a trap into the virtual machine monitor,
都会导致 trap 进入虚拟机监视器，
which costs maybe hundreds of cycles,
可能需要数百个周期，
that means this is slow, this is inefficient
这意味着这是缓慢的，低效的，
and so the difference here is that,
所以这里的不同之处在于，
instead of slavishly mimicking a real device,
不是盲目地模仿真实的设备，
some designers come up with a device interface,
一些设计师设计出一个设备接口，
that's not implemented by any real piece of hardware,
不是由任何真正的硬件实现的，
but only implemented by a virtual machine monitor,
而是仅由虚拟机监视器实现的，
and it just happens to be designed in a way that doesn't require a lot of traps,
而且它是以一种不需要太多 trap 的方式设计的，
instead of chatting with control registers and expecting the device to respond immediately,
不是与控制寄存器交互并期望设备立即响应，
which really requires a trap,
这需要一个 trap ，
instead the device driver and that sort of virtual hardware are decoupled
相反，设备驱动程序和虚拟硬件是解耦的，
and don't ever require sort of immediate interaction.
而且不需要任何即时的交互。
Still, in that case, the guest needs its own like a new driver,
不过，在这种情况下，客户机需要自己新的驱动，
so it's just like the guests will have a driver
所以，这需要客户机拥有驱动程序，
for this model of the disk and that model of the disk
对于这个型号的磁盘和那个型号的磁盘，
and also have a driver for a virtual disk.
并且还具有虚拟磁盘的驱动程序。
Right, and so the xv6 does,
对， xv6 也是如此，
so so then, so if the functionality level,
那么，在功能级别，
you play this game, maybe you can boot any operating system,
你使用这个方案，也许你可以启动任何操作系统，
whereas, if you play this game,
然而，如果使用这个方案，
you can only boot operating systems that have been taught about your virtual devices,
你只能启动知道你的虚拟设备的操作系统，
if you want to use the virtual devices,
如果你想使用虚拟设备，
turns out this is actually a standard,
事实上，这是一个标准，
that's provided by multiple different virtual machine schemes,
由多个不同的虚拟机方案提供的，
so with this,
所以，使用这个，
except for the fact that we never tested it on anything other than QEMU,
除了我们从未在 QEMU 以外的任何设备上进行测试，
this disk driver in xv6 might work,
这个在 xv6 中的驱动程序可以工作，
probably be modified to work on other virtual machines.
可能会被修改以在其他虚拟机上运行。
So if xv6 was compiled for that board,
所以，如果 xv6 是为那个电路板编译的，
that you showed some time in the beginning,
您在课程开始时显示的那样，
in that case, you would have to have a different disk driver
在那种情况下，你必须使用不同的驱动程序，
based on what disk that was running, right.
根据正在运行的磁盘，对吗？
Yeah, yeah, I think you may be able to buy disk interface,
是的，我想你可以买到磁盘接口，
real hardware disk interfaces that now support this interface,
真实硬件磁盘接口来支持这个接口，
but but most disk, most disk drive don't
但是大多数磁盘驱动器不支持，
and we would have to implement a new as you said,
我们必须实现一个新的，像你说的那样，
we have to implement a new disk driver for real piece of hardware.
我们必须为真正的硬件实现一个新的磁盘驱动程序。
Yes.
是的。
Okay.
好的。
Any other questions about devices?
关于设备，还有其他问题吗？
Alright, next topic I wanna talk about hardware support for virtual machines,
好了，下一个话题我想谈谈对虚拟机的硬件支持，
and in particular Intel's VT-x scheme,
特别是英特尔的 VT-x 方案，
so what's motivating what motivated Intel and other hardware providers
那么，促使英特尔和其他硬件提供商
to add direct hardware support for virtual machines is
为虚拟机增加直接硬件支持的动机是，
a, the fact that virtual machine uses pervasive,
a, 虚拟机使用无处不在，
so a lot of their customers were running a lot of virtual machines,
它们的很多客户都在运行大量的虚拟机，
and b, the fact that trap-and-emulate as I just described it,
第二， trap-and-emulate ，正如我刚才所说的那样，
often involves a lot of expensive traps,
通常引起很多昂贵的陷阱，
so it's not particularly efficient,
所以它的效率不是特别高，
and a third sort of less interesting perhaps motivation was that,
第三种不太有趣的可能的动机是，
although the RISC-V is pretty well suited to trap-and-emulate virtualization,
尽管 RISC-V 非常适合 trap-and-emulate 虚拟化，
the x86 Intel's microprocessor has a number of detailed features,
英特尔的 x86 微处理器有许多详细的功能，
which make it actually very difficult possible very difficult to virtualize,
使得它可能很难虚拟化，
and so Intel is also motivated to try to fix that,
所以，英特尔试图解决这一问题，
because so many of his customers wanted to run virtual machine monitors.
因为它的很多客户都想运行虚拟机监视器。
Alright, okay, so this hardware is,
好的，所以这个硬件是，
the main point is to make it be,
重点是它成为，
allow you to build faster virtual machines using hardware support,
允许你使用硬件支持创建更快的虚拟机，
and then another motivation was to make it easier to implement virtual machine,
另一个动机是使虚拟机的实现变得更容易，
and this support has been around for maybe ten years
这种支持可能已经存在了十年，
and is now very, very widely used to build virtual machines.
现在非常广泛地用于构建虚拟机。
Okay, so the basic strategy is that
好的，所以基本策略是
all that virtual state that in my trap-and-emulate scheme,
在我的 trap-and-emulate 方案中的所有虚拟状态，
all the virtual state that was being maintained by the virtual machine monitor just in software,
所有虚拟状态由软件的虚拟机监视器管理，
all that virtual state is going to be going to be implemented in the hardware,
所有虚拟状态都将在硬件中实现，
in these hardware supported schemes,
在这些硬件支持的方案中，
and that will allow guest software to execute privileged instructions,
这将允许客户机软件执行特权指令，
affecting these virtual hardware supported registers directly rather than trapping,
直接影响这些虚拟硬件支持的寄存器，而不是使用 trap ，
so the goal is now that guest will be able to execute privileged instructions, but not trap.
所以，现在的目标是让客户机能够执行特权指令，而不是 trap 。
And, the reason you know,
这个原因是，
so that works is that,
这是有效的，
again, we have a virtual machine monitor
同样，我们有一个虚拟机监视器，
and a guest operating system in user level,
并且有一个在用户级别的客户机操作系统，
and the hardware, now we know that in the hardware,
现在我们知道在硬件中，
we have you know a stvec and all those you know hardware registers,
我们有一个 stvec 和所有那些硬件寄存器，
and there's all the,
这些都是，
when we're running in the virtual new schemes, hardware support schemes,
当我们在新的硬件支持虚拟方案上运行时，
we're running the virtual machine monitor,
我们运行虚拟机监视器，
we just use the real versions of these registers,
我们使用这些寄存器的真实版本，
but the hardware,
但是硬件，
when the virtual machine monitor tells the hardware,
当虚拟机监视器告诉硬件，
look please switch into guest mode,
请切换到客户机模式，
the hardware has a complete separate set of registers,
硬件有一套完整的独立寄存器，
dedicated for use by in guest mode.
专门在客户机模式下使用。
So the guest mode can read and write these registers,
所以客户机模式可以读写这些寄存器，
but it's not,
但它不是，
it's reading it's reading writing its hardware copies of its versions of these registers
它读写这些寄存器的硬件复制版本，
rather than the real registers
而不是真正的寄存器，
and the hardware has you know has some kind of extra checks,
并且硬件有一些额外的检查，
it makes on the the guest operating system can do
它限制客户操作系统所能做的，
to make sure that it can't abuse these registers to escape from the virtual machine.
确保它不会滥用这些寄存器，从虚拟机中逃出来。
This is the basic, this is most of the basic strategy
这是最基本的的策略，
and in the terminology of these hardware supported virtual machine schemes,
并且在这些硬件支持的虚拟机方案的术语中，
the name is Intel [one],
名称是 Intel [One] ，
the name for guest mode is non-root,
客户机模式称为 non-root ，
and the name for host mode, we're using real registers is root,
而我们使用真正寄存器的主机模式称为 root ，
and so there's a set of non-root virtual registers for the virtual machine to use
这里有一组 non-root 虚拟寄存器供虚拟机使用，
and there's a set of registers that are used when we are in root mode.
而这里有一组寄存器我们在 root 模式下使用。
So now when we're running in the guest kernel,
所以现在当我们在客户机内核中运行时，
it can execute any privileged instruction without trapping,
它可以执行任何特权指令，而不使用 trap ，
so when wants to read or write the stvec,
那么当需要读写 stvec 时，
the hardware just that's read or write the non-root copy of the hardware stvec register,
硬件只是读写硬件 stvec 寄存器的 non-root 副本，
and so all this stuff proceeds at full speed without having to trap into VMM,
所以，所有这些东西都在全速运行，而不需要陷入 VMM ，
so it's much faster for code that was incurring a lot of traps.
所以它比出现大量 trap 的代码要快得多。
The, you still have to,
这个，你还是需要，
there's a whole bunch of stuff having involved in configuring this,
配置这个需要很多东西要做，
when the virtual machine monitor wants to create a new virtual machine,
当虚拟机监视器要创建新的虚拟机时，
actually has to tell the hardware,
必须要告诉硬件，
and so there is a down in the virtual machine monitors memory,
所以，在虚拟机监视器内存中，
there's this structure that the virtual machine monitor
有虚拟机监视器结构，
and the VT-x hardware used to communicate
它是 VT-x 硬件用来通信的，
just called VMCS VM control something structure,
被称为 VMCS 虚拟机控制结构，
and when the virtual machine monitor wants to create a new virtual machine,
当虚拟机监视器想要创建新的虚拟机时，
it creates one of these in memory
它在内存中创建一个，
and fills in a bunch of configuration flags
并填充一组配置标志，
and also initial values for all these registers
并对所有这些寄存器的值做初始化，
and then tells the VT-x hardware,
然后告诉 VT-x 硬件，
look I want to start running a new virtual machine,
我想开始运行一个新的虚拟机，
and here's the initial state,
这里是初始状态，
and so these new instructions which the paper mentions,
这些是论文提到的新指令，
there's VMLAUNCH just like a new new machine instruction,
有一个 VMLAUNCH ，就像一个新的机器指令，
which you tell it the address of this and it starts running,
你告诉它这个的地址，它开始运行，
you know starting with these registers,
使用这些寄存器开始，
like starts running the guest kernel,
比如开始运行客户机内核，
and there's also this VMRESUME,
这里还有一个 VMRESUME ，
because sometimes, break out of the kernel back, trap out of kernels at VMM,
因为有时候，会从内核中出来，回到 VMM 中，
and you need to resume it
你需要恢复它，
and then code up here can run a new instruction called VMCALL,
然后这里的代码可以运行一个名为 VMCALL 的新指令，
which sort of intentionally exits from non-root mode,
在某种程度上是退出 non-root 模式，
and basically traps into the virtual machine monitor in root mode.
并且 trap 到 root 模式的虚拟机监视器中。
Right, when the virtual machine monitor
当虚拟机监视器
execute one of these instructions to jump into a guest,
执行这些指令中的一个跳入到客户机中，
the ways that it may come back,
它可能回来的方式，
guest now can execute ordinary privileged instructions without trapping,
客户机现在可以执行普通特权指令而不使用 trap ，
but there's a bunch of reasons
但是，原因有很多，
why you may nevertheless return to the virtual machine mode,
为什么仍然可以返回到虚拟机模式，
one is intentional exit,
一个是故意退出，
but also if the device interrupt goes off,
而且如果设备中断关闭，
like the timer interrupt goes off,
比如定时器中断关闭，
that all the microprocessor will force a trap out of,
所有微处理器将强制陷出，
non-root mode out of the guest into root mode in the virtual machine monitor,
non-root 模式的客户机进入 root 模式，在虚拟机监视器中，
so in general device interrupts trap back into the virtual machine monitor
所以，通常情况下，设备中断返回到虚拟机监视器中，
and so that means that a guest operating system can't hog the CPU,
所以，这意味着客户机操作系统不能占用 CPU ，
every time the timer hardware timer ticks, the virtual machine monitor gets control,
每次定时器硬件到达，虚拟机监视器获得控制，
and if there's multiple guests
如果有多个客户机，
and now basically time-share machine using the timer interrupts among all the different guests.
那么分时计算机使用计时器中断在不同的客户机之间切换。
Okay, so this is basic strategy,
好的，这是基本策略，
basically there's a second set of registers,
基本上有第二组寄存器，
the other, the other big piece of machinery that VT-x provides is page table support,
VT-x 提供的另一个大的机制是页表支持，
you know when operating up here in the guest world,
当在客户机世界里执行时，
we still need a page table,
我们也需要一个页表，
you know we need the page table for two reasons,
我们需要页表有两个原因，
one is the guest kernel wants to be able to configure its own page table,
一个是客户机内核想要能够配置自己的页表，
wants to be able to load cr3
希望能够加载 cr3 ，
which is Intel equivalent of the satp register,
它是英特尔中类似 satp 的寄存器，
so we'd love to be able to
所以，我们希望能够，
or VT-x allows the guest kernel to load any value it likes
或 VT-x 允许客户机内核加载任何值，
into the cr3 register to set the page table,
加载到 cr3 寄存器中以设置页表，
and the hardware actually obey that page table that the guest kernel loads,
并且硬件遵守客户机内核加载的页表，
but we know that can be the, which is fantastic, right,
我们知道这是非常好的，
because now that's going to load a page table without trapping the VMM,
因为现在这可以加载一个页表而不陷入 VMM ，
but we know that we can't just let the guests kernel put anything it likes on its page table,
但是我们知道我们不能让客户机内核把任何东西放到它的页表中，
without,
而不，
because that would allow it to read and write arbitrary memory,
因为这将允许它读写任意内存，
so this VT-x scheme actually has another important register,
所以这个 VT-x 方案有另一个重要的寄存器，
which is in fact part of the sort of real,
实际上是一个真实的，
well, who knows where I should draw, but I'll draw it right here,
我不知道应该画在哪里，但我会画在这里，
the extended page table register
扩展页表寄存器 EPT ，
and the virtual machine,
并且虚拟机，
which points to a page table, right,
EPT 指向一个页表，
that maps, well, maps one kind of address or another kind of address,
它映射到一种或另一种地址，
and the virtual machine monitor sets,
并且虚拟机监视器设置，
when it's about to run a guest kernel,
当它要运行客户机内核时，
it sets up an EPT for that kernel,
它为那个内核设置 EPT ，
tells the hardware look here's the EPT for virtual machine I'm about to run
告诉硬件这是我要运行的虚拟机的 EPT ，
and then jumps into the virtual machine,
然后跳到虚拟机中，
and then the game is that,
然后游戏是，
the MMU on this machine,
这台机器上的 MMU ，
when it's translating a guest virtual address,
当它转换客户机虚拟地址时，
it first translates the guest virtual address to a guest physical address,
它首先将客户机虚拟地址转换为客户机物理地址，
to the guests, the page table the guest sets up,
对于客户机设置的页表，
and then does another translation
然后做另一次转换，
of that guest physical address through the EPT to get a host physical address,
通过 EPT 将客户机物理地址转换为主机物理地址，
and that hardware does that automatically for every memory reference the guest does,
硬件会自动对每个客户机内存引用执行这个操作，
as this double level of translation,
这是两级转换，
and so this again gives the VMM control over
所以，这再次给了 VMM 控制，
what physical memory the guest is allowed to use,
客户机允许使用的物理内存，
the guest can set up any page table it likes
客户机可以设置任何页表，
and can do it quite efficiently,
并且可以非常高效地进行，
because it can directly execute the instructions,
因为它可以直接执行指令，
but it's still constrained by the EPT,
但是它仍然受到 EPT 的约束，
which the VMM configured to
VMM 配置为
be able to only use physical pages that the VMM wants it to use.
只能使用 VMM 让它使用的物理页面。
Any questions about the EPT?
关于 EPT ，有什么问题吗？
Oh, sorry, I have a question about EPT,
哦，抱歉，我有一个关于 EPT 的问题，
about the the second set of registers,
关于第二组寄存器，
so if you have two cores and you want to add two VMMs,
如果你有两个核心，并且你想添加两个 VMM ，
does it, do you get like a third copy of the registers?
你有没有第三组寄存器复制？
Every core has its own set of these registers,
每个核心都有自己的这些寄存器，
every core has a sort of independent,
每个核心都有一个独立的，
independent instance of all this VT-x hardware,
独立的 VT-x 硬件的所有实例，
every core, every core has its own 32 general purpose registers,
每个核心都有自己的 32 个通用寄存器，
its own real control registers and its own virtual registers for guest mode,
它自己的真实控制寄存器和自己的客户机模式虚拟寄存器，
its own, its own EPT.
还有它自己的 EPT 。
So you have two different guests on two different cores,
所以你在两个不同的核心上有两个不同的客户机，
they all have their own every register,
它们都有自己的每个寄存器，
every core has its own.
每个核心都有自己的。
So you need a new VMM too?
所以，你也需要一个新的 VMM ？
Well, I mean, it could just like an ordinary operating system,
好的，我是说，它可以和普通操作系统一样，
like xv6 can support multiple processes
就像 xv6 可以支持多进程，
and it's all the same xv6,
它就像 xv6 一样，
but although, and just like xv6 has a separate struct proc for every process,
就像 xv6 每个进程都有单独的 proc 结构，
or virtual machine monitor would have a separate struct, struct vmm or whatever it is,
虚拟机监视器具有单独的 vmm 结构或什么的，
one for each guest to keep track of that guest information for that guest.
每个客户机一个，用于跟踪客户机信息。
Okay, I see, thank you.
好的，我明白了，谢谢。
Yes.
好的。
And as I mentioned before the switching,
就像我之前提到的切换，
if you have one core and three guest,
如果你有一个核心和三个客户机，
switching can be driven by timer interrupts,
切换可以由定时器中断驱动，
which go to the virtual machine monitor not the guest.
它去往虚拟机监视器，而不是客户机。
Okay.
好的。
More questions about virtual machines,
还有更多关于虚拟机的问题吗，
before I switch to the paper.
在我转到论文之前。
Alright, the paper takes this hardware is a starting point
好的，这篇论文把这个硬件作为一个起点，
and uses it for something else not a virtual machine,
并将其用于其他用途，而不是虚拟机，
so that's a lot of the interest in the papers,
这是论文中非常感兴趣的，
that they took this hardware which is absolutely design just for virtual machines,
他们采用了这种专为虚拟机设计的硬件，
and the paper saying,
这篇论文说，
gosh, we could just use this hardware to do just makes not a virtual machine.
我们可以使用这个硬件来做不只是一个虚拟机。
And what they're, a high-level view of what they're doing is,
他们所做的，从高层次角度来说就是，
they're just, they want to implement the ordinary processes,
他们想要实现普通的进程，
now we're back in just Linux,
现在我们回到 Linux ，
no virtual machines anymore, just Linux,
不再有虚拟机，只有 Linux ，
but assuming VT-x hardware is Dune,
假设 VT-x 硬件是 Dune ，
we have Linux
我们有 Linux ，
and we assume we've loaded the Dune loadable kernel module into Linux,
假设我们将 Dune 可加载内核模块加载到 Linux 中，
now this Dune software is running in supervisor mode
现在 Dune 软件在管理员模式下运行，
as part of the Linux kernel,
作为 Linux 内核的一部分，
but for the most part, we're you know we're running Linux
但在很大程度上，我们运行的是 Linux ，
and we're expecting to run Linux processes.
我们希望运行 Linux 进程。
So the abstraction of trying to support is
所以，这个想要支持的是，
mostly the process abstraction with system calls
大多数使用系统调用的进程
and all the sort of ordinary things that Linux processes can do,
以及所有 Linux 进程可以做的普通事情，
but we want to use this VT-x hardware to give sort of more,
但是我们想使用这个 VT-x 硬件来提供更多，
sort of allow ordinary processes to do some extra things
允许普通进程做一些额外的事情，
and there's really, so we're actually gonna run,
所以我们要运行，
so Dune runs these processes
所以， Dune 运行这些进程，
or allows a process to switch into Dune mode,
或允许进程切换到 Dune 模式，
which means that instead of just being protected being isolated by a page table,
这意味着不只是由页表隔离，
now this process is isolated by the complete VT-x apparatus,
现在这个进程被完整的 VT-x 设备隔离，
so for this process, Dune is going to maintain,
所以，对于这个进程， Dune 将要维护，
this process now has this virtual set of of all the control registers,
这个进程现在具有这个所有虚拟控制寄存器，
like its own cr3 in it
比如它自己的 cr3 ，
and therefore its own page table,
因此，也就有自己的页表，
because this process is going to run in non-root supervisor mode,
因为这个进程将在 non-root 管理员模式下运行，
so it can run all the privileged instructions,
所以它可以运行所有的特权指令，
although against the virtual state implemented by VT-x.
尽管是 VT-x 实现的虚拟状态。
So one of the critical things this process can do under Dune is
所以在 Dune 下，这个进程可以做的一件重要的事情是，
set up its own page table using its own hardware cr3,
使用自己的硬件 cr3 设置自己的页表，
of course Dune you know controls EPT for this process,
当然 Dune 控制着这个进程的 EPT ，
so and the EPT is going to be set up
所以， EPT 被设置为
to only have entries for this process's ordinary process memory,
只有这个进程的普通进程内存的条目，
so the process can put anything that like cr3,
所以这个进程可以放任何像 cr3 的东西，
but because the MMU translates through the EPT,
因为 MMU 通过 EPT 转换，
after translating through the ordinary page table,
再通过普通页表转换，
the process still cannot escape its allocated memory,
这个进程仍然不能跳出给它分配的内存，
so the process does have any sort of additional powers
所以，这个进程有额外能力，
with respect to other processes or kernel memory,
相对于其他进程或内核内存，
it just has now a more flexible way of setting up its own memory.
它现在有了一种更灵活的方式来设置自己的内存。
Alright, so one thing a Dune process can do is have it's own page table,
好的，所以 Dune 进程可以做的一件事就是拥有自己的页表，
in fact, it's basically required to have its own page table,
实际上，它需要有自己的页表，
because otherwise, it won't work,
否则，它就不会起作用了，
and the other thing a process can do is
进程可以做的另一件事是
have a supervisor mode and user mode within its little virtual machine,
在它的小虚拟机中拥有管理员模式和用户模式，
and be able to run,
并且能够运行，
be able to have the supervisor code set itself up to be protected
能够将管理程序代码自身设置为保护，
against the code that runs in guest user mode.
对在访客用户模式下运行的代码。
So the paper really talks about these two different uses,
所以这篇论文谈到了两种不同的用途，
two different things you can do with Dune.
可以用 Dune 做的两件不同的事。
So the this ability to get at,
所以，这个能力可以获得，
for a process to get at the hardware support for supervisor versus user mode,
对于一个进程，获得对管理者模式而不是用户模式的支持，
allows them to run untrusted plugin code here in a sandbox.
允许它们在沙箱中运行不受信任的插件代码。
And so the idea is,
所以这里的想法是，
oh, maybe you're, you're, maybe the main program is like a web browser,
也许主程序是一个网络浏览器，
you know you can download web browser, download plugins that your web browser runs,
你可以下载网络浏览器运行的插件，
maybe a new video decoder
也许是一个新的视频解码器，
or a new ad blocker or something,
或者是新的广告拦截器之类的，
but we don't totally trust that plugin,
但是我们并不完全信任那个插件，
so we'd like to run it with restricted privileges somehow,
所以我们想以某种方式以有限的特权运行它，
it's possible, but a little bit tricky to do in ordinary Linux,
这是可能的，但在普通 Linux 中做起来有点困难，
but with Dune, now we can run the plugin appear in user space,
但是有了 Dune ，我们就可以在用户空间中运行插件，
and the web browser which runs in the in the process supervisor mode
而且在管理者模式下进程中运行的 Web 浏览器，
can configure the page table,
可以配置页表，
configure a different page table,
配置不同的页表，
for use by this user code,
供这个用户代码使用，
because it's allowed write cr3
因为它允许写入 cr3 ，
and that can allow it to run this untrusted plugin code
这允许它运行这个不受信任的插件代码，
with only allowing it restricted access
只允许它受限地访问
to just some pages of the web browser's memory,
Web 浏览器内存中的一些页面，
so that even if plugin code malicious,
这样即使插件代码是恶意的，
can't just arbitrarily read wirte the main web browser's memory,
也不能随意读写主网页浏览器的内存，
and if the user code, user code may be expected to make system calls,
如果用户代码希望进行系统调用，
but those system calls,
但是这些系统调用，
actually trap into the supervisor mode of the process and not into Linux,
实际上陷入进程的管理者模式，而不是 Linux 的，
the user, this plugin code may think it's calling for fork or read or write who knows what,
这个插件代码可能认为它在调用 fork 或读写什么的，
but actually those attempts to execute system calls
但实际上这些执行系统调用的尝试
trap into the web browser in the process,
会陷入 Web 浏览器进程中，
and they can do whatever like,
它们可以做任何事情，
they can not do the system call, execute system call or who knows what,
它们不能执行系统调用，或者别的什么，
our web browser has full control over the sandboxed plugin code.
我们的网络浏览器可以完全控制沙盒的插件代码。
As a quick overview,
作为一个概述，
any any questions about using Dune sandbox?
关于使用 Dune 沙箱，有什么问题吗？
And to be fair, this is something,
公平地说，这是一种，
this is an effect that could be achieved by quite different techniques,
这种效果可以通过使用完全不同的技术来实现，
using existing Linux facilities,
使用现有的 Linux 的设施，
but Dune allows you to provide in a particularly kind of elegant and efficient way
但是 Dune 允许你提供一种特别优雅和高效的方式，
by using the VT-x hardware.
通过使用 VT-x 硬件。
The other thing that the paper talks about using Dune for is
论文讨论的使用 Dune 的另一件事是，
to make garbage collection faster,
使垃圾收集更快，
and here it's,
这里是，
the way it does that is by allowing the garbage collection,
它的工作方式是通过允许垃圾收集，
we're not doing sandbox anymore,
我们不再使用沙盒，
we're actually not even using user mode,
实际上我们甚至不使用用户模式，
we're just having one program,
我们只有一个程序，
we're, we're assuming that we're writing just whatever program who knows what,
假设我们在写任何程序，
but in a garbage collected language,
但是在具有垃圾收集的语言中，
like Java or python or something,
比如 Java 或 Python 之类的，
garbage collection could be slow,
垃圾收集可能会很慢，
you know, there's dozens and dozens of tricks for making garbage collection faster,
有几十种技巧可以让垃圾收集更快，
but one of the things that's important in garbage collectors,
但对垃圾收集者来说，重要的一点是，
the garbage collectors is somewhat,
垃圾收集器有时，
many garbage collectors trace find that memory is still alive, is still active,
许多垃圾收集器跟踪发现内存仍然是活动的，
by just tracing all the pointers through all objects starting at the registers,
通过跟踪从寄存器开始的所有对象的所有指针，
and if doesn't find some object after it's completed trace,
如果在完成跟踪后没有找到一些对象，
then that object can't be reached, is referred to by any pointer,
那么无法到达的对象，没有任何指针关联的，
it could be freed.
它可以被释放。
But many garbage collectors run at the same time
但是许多垃圾收集器同时运行，
as in a different thread or something as the main program,
与主程序在不同的线程或其他地方，
and so maybe the garbage collector has started tracing
所以可能垃圾收集器已经开始跟踪
pointers from maybe from some set of registers,
来自某组寄存器的指针，
and this followed a pointer to this object,
在这个对象之后有一个指针，
which had pointers these objects,
有指向这些对象的指针，
and the garbage collectors following each of these pointers,
并且垃圾收集器跟随这些指针中的每一个，
down to the tree or graph of objects,
向下到达对象的树或图，
may be the garbage collector has gone down here so far,
可能垃圾收集器已经到这里了，
and actually trace through all these objects,
并且跟踪所有这些对象，
but then because the garbage collector is running concurrently with the program itself,
但是因为垃圾收集器与程序本身同时运行，
maybe the program modifies this object, the garbage collectors already traced through,
也许程序修改了这个对象，垃圾收集器已经追踪过的，
that's a bad deal,
这是一个糟糕的处理，
because now the list of object pointers,
因为现在对象指针列表，
that garbage collectors decided alive or dead or whatever,
垃圾收集器决定是活的还是死的或其他的，
it may not be correct,
它可能是不正确的，
because the object is already seen has been modified by the program.
因为看过的对象已经被程序修改。
So, Dune using page table support
所以， Dune 使用页表支持，
provides a way for the garbage collector to detect writes like that,
为垃圾收集器提供一种检测这种写入的方法，
and in particular Dune sets up the cr3, the virtual cr3 supported by VT-x
特别是 Dune 设置 VT-x 支持的虚拟 cr3 ，
to point to its own page table,
指向它自己的页表，
and then the leaves all these page table entries valid,
然后使所有这些页表条目有效，
but it looks at the d bit, every page table entry has a dirty bit,
但是它查看 d 位，每个页表条目有一个脏位，
that in the case, there's been a write to that page,
在这种情况下，对这页进行了写入，
so if the program writes some object,
如果程序写入某个对象，
then the dirty bit in the corresponding page,
那么相应页面中的脏位，
in the page table, the dirty bit will be set,
在页表中，脏位将会设置，
and so the garbage collectors finished tracing through the objects,
所以，垃圾收集器完成了对这些物体的追踪，
it goes back and looks at the d bits in the page table,
它返回并查看页表中的 d 位，
defined all pages that contain objects that might have been modified
定义包含可能已修改的对象的所有页面，
and re-scans those objects,
并重新扫描这些对象，
and it turns out that this facility of getting at the d bits
事实证明，这种获取 d 位的能力，
is difficult and slow with ordinary Linux,
对于普通 Linux 来说是困难和缓慢的，
I don't even know if Linux supports,
我甚至不知道 Linux 是否支持，
there are operating systems where you can make system calls to ask for d bits,
有些操作系统可以进行系统调用来请求 d 位，
but if you use Dune and VT-x,
但是如果你使用 Dune 和 VT-x ，
then the process could just use ordinary load and store instructions
然后，这个进程可以只使用普通的加载和存储指令
to get the PTEs and therefore the d bits and it's very fast.
来获得 PTE 和 d 位，并且非常快。
And so they showed you know that,
所以他们展示了，
this makes this trick for some programs that are garbage collection intensive,
这个技巧对于一些垃圾收集密集型的程序来说，
makes the programs significantly faster.
大大加快了程序的运行速度。
Any questions?
有什么问题吗？
What would happen if a sandbox program wants to,
如果沙箱程序想要，
like run its own garbage collector or something, like that?
运行自己的垃圾收集器或类似的东西，会发生什么？
I see, so you're sort of using,
我明白了，所以你使用，
alright, alright,
好的，
so we got using Dune,
所以，我们开始使用 Dune ，
we have a Dune process,
我们有一个 Dune 进程，
that's actually using VT-x is a supervisor versus user mode,
它使用 VT-x 是管理员模式而不是用户模式，
we're running a plugin up here in user mode,
我们在用户模式下运行一个插件，
and the plugin it also it's also written in a garbage collected language
但是插件也是用垃圾收集语言编写的，
and would like to use to have its own page table,
并且希望使用它自己的页表，
its own cr3 point to its own page table with its own d bits.
它自己的 cr3 指向它自己的包含 d 位的页表。
No, that doesn't work,
不，那不能工作，
because we're going to run,
因为我们将要运行，
the way Dune wants you to run plugins sandbox plugins is
Dune 希望你运行沙箱插件的方式是，
to run them and used in guest user mode,
运行它们并在客户机用户模式下使用它们，
guest user mode is not allowed,
客户机用户模式不允许，
it's just like user mode is not allowed to think about cr3,
就像用户模式不允许考虑 cr3 ，
and so in user mode in guest user mode,
所以，在客户机模式下，
we don't get to have our own page table,
我们不能拥有自己的页表，
and so we don't get quick access to the d bits,
所以我们不能快速访问这个 d 位，
it's only in guest supervisor mode,
它只在客户机管理者模式下。
though we can have our own cr3,
我们可以有自己的 cr3 ，
so you can't,
所以你不能，
well, there's no obvious way to combine the two tricks,
没有明显的方法来结合这两种技巧，
the two kinds of tricks Dune allows.
Dune 允许的两种技巧。
What about let's say somebody wrote a browser actually using Dune,
假设某人写了一个浏览器使用了 Dune ，
that would mean like,
那就是说，
that would be quite tough to make,
那就很难做了，
if some computers didn't support Dune or something right,
如果有些计算机不支持 Dune 之类的东西，
like it's hard to just put Chrome into and to use Dune,
比如，让 Chrome 使用 Dune 很难，
if not everyone has that kernel modules.
不是每个计算机都有那样的内核模块。
Right, so first of all you have to be running on a computer that supports the VT-x,
好的，首先你必须在一台支持 VT-x 的计算机上运行，
you know the underlying computer support VT-x,
底层计算机支持 VT-x ，
which means many Intel chips, many.
这意味着很多英特尔芯片，很多。
So, if you need VT-x to run Dune
所以，如果你需要 VT-x 来运行 Dune ，
and Dune had to be loaded
必须加载 Dune ，
in order to run the browser that takes advantage of Dune,
才能运行利用 Dune 的浏览器，
so yeah, you've got to set this up correctly.
所以，是的，你必须正确地设置它。
You know it's a research project,
这是个研究项目，
it's intended to sort of get people thinking about
它的目的是让人们思考
things that could be deployed in the real world,
可以在现实世界中部署的东西，
if they were, they seem like they're valuable,
它们看起来很有价值，
so you know just like Linux
所以就像 Linux ，
and Linux is hundreds and hundreds of features it has,
Linux 有成百上千的功能，
and so somebody decided to add Dune to Linux you know as a standard feature,
所以，有人决定将 Dune 添加到 Linux 中作为一个标准功能，
then that could start relying on,
然后可以依赖它，
Chrome could just use it would not be a problem.
Chrome 直接使用它就不成问题了。
Sorry, so in a high-level,
抱歉，从高层级上看，
Dune this like, like be like making a VM,
Dune 像是创建了一个虚拟机，
but instead of VM you are run a process.
但运行的不是虚拟机，而是运行一个进程。
Or yeah or, yeah, you can phrase it either way,
或者，是的，你可以用任何一种方式来表达，
it's, I mean, it's it's it's supporting what's mostly a process abstraction,
我的意思是，它支持的是进程的抽象，
but but but, it's using instead of using a page table hardware,
但是它使用的不是页表硬件，
it's using the CPU hardware to support a process abstraction,
它使用 CPU 硬件来支持进程抽象，
but instead of that particular CPU hardware,
但是它使用的不是特定的 CPU 硬件，
it's using is the VT-x hardware,
而是使用 VT-x 硬件，
which as a few extra features,
作为一些额外的功能，
like, like the ability to set up your own page.
比如，能够设置自己的页面。
Right, right, I see,
好的，我明白了，
I remember the paper I read process level abstraction,
我记得论文，我读过流程级别的抽象，
but I didn't understand what it means,
但我不明白它的意思，
but now I understand it, thank you.
不过，我现在明白了，谢谢。
Alright, now time is up,
好的，现在时间到了，
I'm happy to continue,
我很高兴继续，
anybody has more questions, happy to answer.
任何人有更多的问题，很乐意回答。
Yeah, so I had a question,
是的，所以我有个问题，
in particular about a something that said in the paper was,
特别是关于论文中说的一个东西是，
if a Dune like a process a process inside Dune forks,
如果一个 Dune 中的进程 fork ，
it becomes a non Dune process,
它变成了一个非 Dune 进程，
isn't that like a security flying away or or.
这是不是安全跳出，或者。
What's the attack?
攻击是什么？
Well, if you run something as a Dune process,
如果你将某项内容作为 Dune 进程运行，
thinking that it's now safe,
认为它现在是安全的，
but then it can run, it can just fork escape.
但是然后它运行，从 fork 逃脱。
So, here's a possibility,
所以，这是一种可能性，
okay, so if let's see code done in supervisor mode,
好的，如果代码在管理者模式下完成，
there's no security problems,
这里没有安全问题，
this reflected this code,
这些代码，
because you already have whatever privileges where possible it already has,
因为你已经拥有一些权限，
it does not gain the extra privilege just fork.
它不会获得额外的特权，只是 fork 。
Okay.
好的。
Code up, but maybe it's using Dune sandbox plugin,
编写代码，也许它使用的是 Dune 沙盒插件，
and we have untrusted code up here,
我们这里有不可信的代码，
that, that would be dangerous, you know, let it run without Dune,
让它在没有 Dune 的情况下运行是很危险的，
because it's not trusted, we're using Dune sandbox,
因为它是不可信的，我们使用 Dune 沙盒，
so then if we forked,
所以如果我们 fork ，
okay, so this code cannot fork, right,
好的，所以这个代码不能 fork ，
you can try to call the fork system call,
你可以尝试调用 fork 系统调用，
but a system call instruction here traps into the supervisor part of this process,
但是这里的系统调用指令会陷入这个进程的管理者部分，
and presuming the supervisor part of this process is carefully written not to be tricked
假设这一进程的管理者部分是精心编写的，不会被骗，
and so it's not actually a fork.
所以它不是真正的 fork 。
So that doesn't work,
所以这是行不通的，
if the supervisor of code,
如果管理者代码，
it is allowed to fork,
它允许被 fork ，
it is allowed to make system calls
它允许进行系统调用，
that you get to fork this process with the same memory image,
你可以 fork 这个进程，使用相同的内存镜像，
so we'll get the plugin up here, and.
所以我们会把插件放在这里，然后。
I see.
我明白了。
If you didn't realize that fork turned off Dune,
如果你没有意识到 fork 关掉了 Dune ，
and it did,
而且，
I mean it's hard to see how this could actually happen,
我的意思是很难想象这是怎么发生的，
but you know if it did something to resume execution of the plugin,
如果它要恢复插件的执行，
now that would be very foolish,
那将是非常愚蠢的，
you know the plugin is a sandbox,
那个插件是一个沙盒，
you know, in fact this you know the code jump in the sandbox here
事实上，代码跳入沙箱中的这里，
involves privileged instructions,
涉及特权指令，
just like it does on this slide,
就像这张幻灯片上一样，
because it switches, switches guest modes,
因为它切换客户机模式，
and if you execute that instruction here,
如果你在这里执行那条指令，
that's illegal instruction.
那是非法指令。
I guess, I guess what I was misunderstanding was,
我想我误解的是，
I think that the plugin is not a process,
我认为插件不是一个进程，
like the the Dune process is the sandbox, the plugin is just inside there,
比如 Dune 进程就是沙盒，插件就在里面，
process is just enabled to use features
进程只是可以使用功能，
to let the plugin run faster, basically.
来让插件运行得更快。
That's right, you know we're absolutely assuming that this software down here is clever,
是的，我们假设下面的这个软件是聪明的，
which is careful about what it likes,
它会小心，
about preventing a sandbox to actually work in real life.
防止沙箱在现实生活中执行。
And it's not, it's not unsafe, for the Dune process to have supervisor mode,
它不是不安全的，对于 Dune 进程有管理者模式，
because it's actually supervisor mode in non-root mode,
因为它实际上是 non-root 模式下的管理员模式，
which is the same as supervisor mode and a guest OS, right.
与管理者模式一样，在客户机操作系统中。
It's like you can let it do everything,
比如你可以让它做任何事情，
just, but because VT-x it's going to be like a virtual machine,
但是因为 VT-x 将会像一个虚拟机，
so it's not going to hurt us.
所以它不会伤害我们。
That's right, it can't escape from its address spaces,
没错，它无法从它的地址空间讨论，
EPT, is Dune a set of EPT to constrain it to its address space.
Dune ，一组 EPT 将其约束到它的地址空间。
That makes sense.
理解了。
So one last thing I had,
所以我还有最后一件事，
I I there was like a paragraph on on EPTs
有一段是关于 EPT 的，
and it said that the user page table can just expand the addresses
它说用户页表可以扩展地址，
like re-map them to their original layout,
比如将它们重新映射到原来的布局，
that was something I just didn't understand the whole paragraph.
我不明白整段话的意思。
So, I I don't.
所以，我不知道。
Maybe that's a bit specific.
也许这有点太具体了。
I think what's going on is that
我认为是，
the physical addresses are on the x86 are have fewer bits than virtual addresses,
x86 上的物理地址比虚拟地址具有更少的位数，
so I'm kind of guessing,
所以我在猜测，
and so that means that the EPT you know that,
这意味着 EPT ，
the ordinary page table maps virtual addresses to physical addresses,
普通页表将虚拟地址映射到物理地址，
that physical addresses have fewer bits
物理地址有更少的位，
and so that constructs the the,
所以这就构成了，
that means, when Dune is setting up,
也就是说，当 Dune 设置的时候，
an address space for a process
进程的地址空间，
or one way to look at is
或者一种方式是，
when Dune setting up the address space for process,
当 Dune 为进程设置地址空间时，
the process address space has to fit in the smaller number of bits for a Dune process.
进程地址空间必须适合 Dune 进程的较小位数。
Okay.
好的。
Regular process is going to be used,
普通进程将使用，
I don't know what the numbers are,
我不知道数字是多少，
let's say 48 bit virtual addresses,
比如 48 位虚拟地址，
but maybe physical addresses are only 36 bits,
但也许物理地址只有 36 位，
again, I'm making this up.
同样，这是我编造的。
The ordinary process could use all 48 bits for virtual addresses,
普通进程可以使用所有 48 位用于虚拟地址，
a Dune process can only use 36 or whatever.
而 Dune 进程只能使用 36 位或其他位。
So there's different rules for things have to fit down.
所以有不同的规则来适合。
Okay.
好的。
I had a question about the VT-x scheme
我对 VT-x 方案有一个问题，
and how we're accessing page tables,
以及我们如何访问页表，
so when like in the way we're accessing page tables,
比如，当我们使用这种方式访问页表时，
because we're going to the EPT
因为我们要去 EPT ，
and then doing the second layer of translation there,
然后在那里进行第二次转换，
from the guest physical address to the host physical address,
从客户物理地址到主机物理地址，
is the latency of accesses to the page table actually lower?
是不是访问页表的延迟变得更低？
It takes more time potentially takes more time possibly,
可能需要更多时间，
much more time to for the hardware MMU translated address,
对于硬件 MMU ，使用更多时间来转换地址，
because now it has to do two,
因为现在它也必须做两次，
well, the the worst cases very much worse,
最糟糕的情况要糟糕得多，
because, you know on the RISC-V,
因为，你知道在 RISC-V 上，
there's multiple levels of the page table
页表有多个级别，
and so the MMU be generated from this page from this page table page,
所以 MMU 生成从这个页表，
and then next and next,
然后是下一层，下一层，
each of those the xv6 also has multiple levels,
xv6 中的每一个也具有多个级别，
and so in the xv6,
所以，在 xv6 中，
in the lookup, in the first, in the main page table,
在查找中，在第一个主页表中，
also has to make multiple memory references potentially,
可能还必须进行多个内存引用，
each of those multiple memory references has to go through the EPT
多个内存引用中的每一个都必须通过 EPT ，
and the EPT is also a multilevel page table,
而 EPT 也是多级页表，
and so I don't even know what the worst case number of memory references,
所以我甚至不知道最坏情况下的内存引用数量，
but it's quite a bit worse under VT-x
但在 VT-x 下就更糟了，
and it is with not that it is ordinary cases,
这并不是普通的情况，
so there's potential there and in fact there's lots of caching,
所以可能，事实上有很多缓存，
so usually don't run up against that worst case, but.
所以通常不会遇到最坏的情况，但是。
And so virtual machines are they still like generally slow today,
今天的虚拟机总体上仍然很慢，
and if so, I I guess I was wondering how does AWS work,
如果是这样的话，我想知道 AWS 是如何运作的，
if it seems to be fast and it seems to be working well, so.
如果它看起来很快，而且运行得很好，那么。
Yeah, my my belief is that they use VT-x hardware,
是的，我相信他们用的是 VT-x 硬件，
they use the support that we're talking about
他们使用我们所说的支持，
and that is as well as clever device schemes for efficient device access,
这也是实现高效设备访问的聪明的设备方案，
and that the result is that AWS virtual machines are fast,
结果是 AWS 虚拟机速度很快，
or not much slower than a real computer.
或者比真正的电脑慢不了多少。
Cool thank you so much.
好的，非常感谢。
Oh, I had also another question on the shadow copy for trap-and-emulate,
哦，我还有一个关于 trap-and-emulate 影子拷贝的问题，
so you said that it like,
所以你说它就像，
I understand how you would make it,
我知道你会怎么做，
but does it actually make the shadow copy or does it just,
但它是真的制作影子副本，还是只是，
I think it has to be the shadow copy right,
我认为它必须是影子复制，
because it has to allow the process just to do it itself,
因为它必须让这个进程自己完成，
not like to goes to all the traps,
而不是去所有的 trap ，
but it's doing every time, does it remember the previous.
它每次做，是否记得前一次。
Okay yeah, so yeah, so yeah, yes and yes,
好的，所以是的，是的，是的，
the virtual machine monitor has to create a new page table or there,
虚拟机监视器必须创建新的页表，
you know, yes, has to create a new page table
是的，必须创建一个新的页表，
and its virtual machine monitor's page table
它的虚拟机监视器的页表，
which formatted up which is what the real hardware uses,
格式化为真实硬件使用的，
now of course there are plenty of opportunities for caching and for reuse,
当然，有很多缓存和重用的机会，
so it's a it's a clever virtual machine monitors,
所以它是一个聪明的虚拟机监视器，
if they notice that oh the guest changed just one PTE,
如果它们注意到，客户机修改了一个 PTE ，
then the virtual machine monitor may be able to
那么虚拟机监视器可能能够
correspondingly limited amount of work to update its shadow page table.
相应地有限的工作来更新它的影子页面。
And it also may keep,
它可能也会保留，
you know when if it's sort of multiplexing time sharing among multiple virtual machines,
如果它是多个虚拟机之间的分时复用，
the virtual machine monitor will keep around
虚拟机监视器将保持
the shadow page tables for the virtual machines that aren't running,
未运行的虚拟机的影子页表，
so that it can reuse them directly,
这样它可以直接重用它们，
when it switches back to that virtual machine.
在切换回那个虚拟机时。
Okay I see,
好的，我明白了，
so does that mean that you have,
那是不是意味着你必须，
like, you have to remember a shadow copy
比如，你必须记住每个影子副本，
for like each process for each virtual machine.
为每个虚拟机的每个进程。
Yes, there are many, many, many, many page tables
是的，有很多页表，
running around on the virtual machine,
运行在虚拟机上，
virtual machine is aware of all page table switches that the guest does.
虚拟机知道客户机执行的所有页表切换。
Yeah, it's, that the specific issue of maintaining the shadow page tables,
维护影子页表的具体问题，
it has consumed a lot of work.
它消耗了大量的工作。
Right, thank you so much.
好的，非常感谢。
Before you know this is one of the many things
这是其中之一，
that hardware supported virtual machines,
硬件支持虚拟机，
made quite a bit easier.
变得容易多了。
Oh, okay, okay,
哦，好的，好的，
I see, I see, okay.
我明白了，好的。
Because EPTs means you don't have to cook up your own shadow page.
因为 EPT 意味着你不需要编造自己的影子页面。
Right, right, right, yeah that's nice, yeah, thank you.
好的，很好，谢谢。
Yes.
好的。
Alright, I gotta head up,
好的，我得走了，
but I'll see you guys on Wednesday, thank you.
但我们周三见，谢谢。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Is it okay, if you have time for one more question,
如果你有时间，再问一个问题，
if if if this one is about the garbage collection,
如果这是关于垃圾收集的，
of how like re-scans to see like the dirty bits,
如何重新扫描才能看到脏位，
like it is like a sort of a continued process
它像是一个持续的进程，
where like it continues to re-scan like indefinitely,
它持续无限期地重新扫描，
because, could it.
因为，它能不能。
You're asking, yeah, whatever terminate,
你在问，什么是结束，
supposing oh, there's always something new modified,
因为总会有新的修改，
so in fact this potential problem,
所以实际上这个潜在的问题，
in fact the garbage collector does is it,
垃圾收集器所做的是，
it does one pass, one pass through to completion,
它做一次，完成一次，
and then it freezes everything else, but the garbage collector,
它冻结了所有其他东西，除了垃圾收集器，
so nothing else can happen,
所以不会有其他事情发生，
then it goes back and look at the dirty pages,
然后它会返回并查看脏页，
but of course everything else is frozen
当然，其他一切都会被冻结，
with no more no more dirty pages can occur,
不会再出现脏页，
and then the garbage, the garbage collector looks all dirty pages,
然后垃圾收集器查找所有脏页，
then it knows it's done yet,
然后它知道它已经完成了，
you know does whatever it's supposed to do to finish up
完成它任何它应该做的事情，
and create a free listing
并创建一个空闲列表，
resumes all the threads they had stopped.
并恢复所有它们已经停止的线程。
Oh, okay, yeah, okay, that makes a lot of sense,
哦，好的，好的，这很有道理，
I I don't know it froze everything else, but.
我不知道它冻结了其他的一切，但是。
Yeah yeah, this is complex stuff
是的，这是很复杂的东西，
and of course there's not enough room in the paper Dune paper
当然 Dune 论文中没有足够的篇幅
to explain all the ins and outs what garbage collectors have to, sadly.
来解释垃圾收集器的所有细节。
Alright, yeah, thank you so much.
好的，非常感谢。
Thank you, see you later.
谢谢，再见。